<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<document id="PMC3076731" note="">
    <text xml:space="preserve">Title
Effect of oxandrolone and timing of pubertal induction on final height in Turner’s syndrome: randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial
Abstract

        Objective To examine the effect of oxandrolone and the timing of pubertal induction on final height in girls with Turner’s syndrome receiving a standard dose of growth hormone.
        Design Randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial.
        Setting 36 paediatric endocrinology departments in UK hospitals.
        Participants Girls with Turner’s syndrome aged 7-13 years at recruitment, receiving recombinant growth hormone therapy (10 mg/m2/week).
        Interventions Participants were randomised to oxandrolone (0.05 mg/kg/day, maximum 2.5 mg/day) or placebo from 9 years of age. Those with evidence of ovarian failure at 12 years were further randomised to oral ethinylestradiol (year 1, 2 µg daily; year 2, 4 μg daily; year 3, 4 months each of 6, 8, and 10 μg daily) or placebo; participants who received placebo and those recruited after the age of 12.25 years started ethinylestradiol at age 14.
        Main outcome measure Final height.
        Results 106 participants were recruited, of whom 14 withdrew and 82/92 reached final height. Both oxandrolone and late pubertal induction increased final height: by 4.6 (95% confidence interval 1.9 to 7.2) cm (P=0.001, n=82) for oxandrolone and 3.8 (0.0 to 7.5) cm (P=0.05, n=48) for late pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol. In the 48 children who were randomised twice, the effects on final height (compared with placebo and early induction of puberty) of oxandrolone alone, late induction alone, and oxandrolone plus late induction were similar, averaging 7.1 (3.4 to 10.8) cm (P&lt;0.001). No cases of virilisation were reported.
        Conclusion Oxandrolone had a positive effect on final height in girls with Turner’s syndrome treated with growth hormone, as did late pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol at age 14 years. However, these effects were not additive, so using both had no advantage. Oxandrolone could, therefore, be offered as an alternative to late pubertal induction for increasing final height in Turner’s syndrome.
        Trial registration Current Controlled Trials ISRCTN50343149.
      


    
      Introduction
      Turner’s syndrome can be defined as absence or abnormality of the second X chromosome in a major cell line in a phenotypic female. The phenotype is highly variable, but short stature and gonadal dysgenesis are usually present. Short stature in Turner’s syndrome relates to impairment of each phase of the infancy-childhood-puberty model of growth,1 and it results in a mean untreated final height approximately 21 cm below that of the unaffected female population.2 The mainstay of treatment for short stature is recombinant growth hormone, available since 1985 and licensed for use in Turner’s syndrome. Studies have shown its efficacy in improving height velocity and final height, although individual outcomes vary markedly.3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
      The adjunctive use in Turner’s syndrome of the anabolic steroid oxandrolone remains controversial. When given in combination with growth hormone treatment, some studies have reported improved final height,6 11 12 whereas others have reported little or no effect.13 14 15 The high doses used in early studies were associated with virilisation,6 12 14 and even low doses, as reported in a recent Dutch publication, may be problematic.15 These potential adverse effects must be balanced against potential improvement in growth.
      Most girls with Turner’s syndrome need oestrogen therapy during adolescence to induce pubertal development.16 However, the optimal age at which to begin remains controversial; some people advocate a delay to extend the growth period and increase final height,5 6 17 18 whereas others have highlighted psychological problems of delaying pubertal development, suggesting that the benefits are marginal.19 The British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes recognised the uncertainties relating to the use of oxandrolone and timing of pubertal induction and set up the UK Turner Study in 1999 to investigate them.
    
    
      Methods
      
        Participants
        Members of the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes recruited patients from participating paediatric endocrinology departments in UK hospitals. Inclusion criteria for participation of patients were karyotype confirmed Turner’s syndrome (all karyotypes were eligible, including mosaic), age 7-13 years, no previous growth hormone treatment or previous treatment in the range 8.3-11.7 mg/m2/week in five to seven injections a week, no previous oxandrolone and oestrogen therapy, and open epiphyses. Exclusion criteria were major systemic illness that might affect growth and social or psychological difficulties likely to seriously impair concordance.
      
      
        Study design
        We devised a double blind, placebo controlled, randomised controlled trial, including two randomisations in a two by two factorial design. Figure 1 shows the flow chart of the design and participants. A steering committee (British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials/Audit Group) supervised the study, and an independent data and safety monitoring group was established. All participants’ parents gave written informed consent.
         Fig 1 Flow chart of participation in UK Turner Study according to treatment groups, completions, and withdrawals. *Withdrawn before 12 years of age (that is, randomised only at randomisation 1 to oxandrolone or placebo). †Aged ≥12.25 years at recruitment; oestrogen treatment started at 14 years with no randomisation. ‡Withdrawn after 12 years of age (that is, randomised at randomisation 1 to oxandrolone or placebo and at randomisation 2 if oestrogen treatment needed)
      
      
        Randomisation and masking
        The British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials Unit (Cambridge, UK) used minimisation by weighted randomisation for the study’s two randomisations.20 Randomisation 1, to oxandrolone or placebo, took place at age 9 years (or at enrolment, if older) and was balanced for enrolling centre, quarter of mid-parental height, and previous exposure to growth hormone treatment. Randomisation 2 took place at age 12 years in girls with ovarian failure (basal serum follicle stimulating hormone concentration &gt;10 U/L), with additional minimisation for randomisation 1, to begin oral ethinylestradiol or placebo at 12 years; the placebo group subsequently started ethinylestradiol at 14 years. Girls with a follicle stimulating hormone concentration below 10U/L and a karyotype associated with preservation of ovarian function (45,X/46,XX and 45,X/47,XXX21) (the spontaneous puberty group) were not randomised at randomisation 2. Girls with other karyotypes were tested for concentrations of gonadotrophin releasing hormone and were randomised at randomisation 2 if the peak follicle stimulating hormone concentration was above 30 U/L. Participants enrolled after the age of 12.25 years and without spontaneous puberty (the late group) started ethinylestradiol at 14 years.
      
      
        Treatment
        All participants received the growth hormone preparation of their choice at 10 mg/m2/week in daily subcutaneous injections. Oral oxandrolone (SPA, Milan, Italy) was given at 0.05 mg/kg/day, with a maximum daily dose of 2.5 mg. Oral ethinylestradiol (UCB Pharma, Slough, UK) was given daily as follows, regardless of the age at starting: year 1, 2 μg; year 2, 4 μg; year 3, four months each of 6, 8, and 10 μg. The code for randomisation 2 was broken at 15 years to allow introduction of progesterone therapy: oral norethisterone (CP Pharmaceuticals, Wrexham, UK) 5 mg daily for five days each month.
        Treatment with growth hormone and oxandrolone continued until final height was reached. Oestrogen/progesterone therapy continued at an adult replacement dose once pubertal induction was completed.
        White, uncoated, flat bevelled edge placebo tablets (7 and 5 mm in diameter) (Essential Nutrition, Brough, UK) were specially manufactured to match the size, weight, and appearance of oxandrolone 2.5 mg and ethinylestradiol 2 µg tablets respectively. The study’s central pharmacy (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Glasgow, UK) supplied all tablets in a double blind, placebo controlled fashion; only staff at the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials Unit and the central distributing pharmacy were not blinded to treatment allocations.
      
      
        Oxandrolone supplies
        In 2004 and 2008, the sole European manufacturer of oxandrolone 2.5 mg ceased production, resulting in 34 participants in 2004 and 11 in 2008 temporarily suspending active oxandrolone treatment (mean duration: 2004, 52 days; 2008, 163 days). In 2008, the decision was taken to terminate the treatment arm forthwith, resulting in eight participants stopping oxandrolone treatment prematurely.
      
      
        Study procedures
        At clinic visits every four to six months, height was measured with a Harpenden stadiometer to the last completed 1 mm and converted to an SD score by using the British 1990 reference.22 Radiographs of the left wrist were obtained annually, and a single observer (WFP) analysed them for bone age estimation according to the Tanner Whitehouse II method.23 Biochemical analyses followed local protocols, and the results were reported centrally.
        Standardised pharmacovigilance procedures were followed, with recording of adverse events or reactions at each visit and subsequent review by the Data and Safety Monitoring Group. Data collection ceased if participants withdrew consent, although we included previously collected data in the analysis.
      
      
        Statistical methods
        The primary outcome was final height, defined as height velocity less than 1 cm/year and bone age at least 15.5 years. Secondary outcomes were maximum height (that is, the most recently available height), age of attaining final height, and the three summary growth parameters from the SITAR analysis described below.
        Assuming a standard deviation of 5 cm, we needed 50 girls in each group to detect a difference between groups in mean final height of 2.8 cm with 80% power at 5% significance—a total of 100 patients. The study was not formally powered to detect a significant interaction between the two randomisations. In the event, more than 100 patients were recruited, but fewer than 100 were followed up to final height.
        We estimated the effects of the two randomisations separately by using multiple regression. We also adjusted randomisation 2 (timing of pubertal induction) for randomisation 1 (oxandrolone) and tested for an interaction.
        In addition, we applied SITAR (superimposition by translation and rotation), a novel method of growth curve analysis, to the data.24 SITAR transforms individual growth curves so that they become essentially the same as each other and, when superimposed, define the average summary curve. To achieve this, each individual curve is suitably altered in three distinct ways: the curve is shifted up/down (a measure of the child’s size in cm) and left/right (a measure of growth tempo in years), and the age axis is stretched/squashed (a measure of percentage velocity). Size, tempo, and velocity are thus participant specific random effects summarising how each girl’s curve differs from the average curve. The effects of the randomisations can be explored by comparing the values of the random effects by trial arm. Equally, separate summary curves can be constructed for each trial arm.
      
    
    
      Results
      One hundred and six girls with Turner’s syndrome were recruited from 36 UK hospitals between 1999 and 2003, of whom 14 withdrew (four of them because of early organisational errors), leaving 92 to complete the study (fig 1). The breakdown of karyotypes was 45,X (39), 45,X/46,XX (18), 45,X/46,XrX (9), complex mosaics containing three or more cell lines (8), 45,X/46,XiX (7), 45,X/45,XY (7), 46,XX including a structural abnormality of second X (7), 45,X/46,XY including a structural abnormality of Y (3), 45,X/46,XX including a structural abnormality of second X (3), 45,X/47,XXX (2), and other (3).
      All 106 participants were randomised at or after 9 years of age to oxandrolone or placebo (randomisation 1), and 60 were also randomised at 12 years to early or late induction of puberty (randomisation 2). Of the 46 girls not randomised at 12 years, 21 enrolled after 12 years (the late group), 18 had spontaneous puberty, and seven had withdrawn before the age of 12 years.
      
        Final and maximum height
        Table 1 shows participants’ characteristics at enrolment, at maximum height, and at final height by treatment group. At the time of writing, 82 participants had attained a mean final height of 151.8 (SD 6.4) cm, and 10 others continued growing. Table 2 shows details of final height and maximum height according to the study’s two randomisations.
        Table 1  Characteristics of participants at enrolment, maximum height, and final height, according to treatment group. Values are mean (SD) unless stated otherwise
        Table 2  Final height and maximum height data for participants randomised twice, according to randomisation 1 (oxandrolone/placebo) and randomisation 2 (pubertal induction at 14/12 years). Values are mean (SD)
        By twice randomised group, the mean final heights were placebo/early induction 147.0 cm, placebo/late induction 153.1 cm, oxandrolone/early induction 154.4 cm, and oxandrolone/late induction 155.1 cm (table 1). Table 3 summarises the results of the randomised comparisons. For randomisation 1, final height was significantly greater with oxandrolone than placebo (4.6 cm, 95% confidence interval 1.9 to 7.2; P=0.001). Similarly, for randomisation 2, final height was significantly greater with pubertal induction at 14 years than at 12 years (3.8 cm, 0.0 to 7.5; P=0.05).
        Table 3  Effects of two randomisations, their interaction, and their combination, on mean final height and mean maximum height
        However, the positive effects of oxandrolone and late induction were not additive. Among girls previously randomised to oxandrolone, the effect of late induction compared with early induction was clinically insignificant (+0.7 cm); in the placebo group, however, late induction added 6.2 cm compared with early induction (table 3, interaction). The two treatments together were thus no more effective than either one alone, as shown by the substantial and close to significant negative interaction. The mean effect on final height of oxandrolone, late induction of puberty, or both compared with placebo and early induction was +7.1 cm (that is, the mean final height in the combined oxandrolone/early, oxandrolone/late, and placebo/late groups compared with the placebo/early group), which is appreciably larger than the effects for either randomisation alone (table 3, combination). This was because the randomisation analyses compared intervention and control groups in which half of each control group had received an effective intervention from the other randomisation, thus reducing the apparent effect size. The standard deviation for the combined group was 5.1 cm, rather less than the 7.4 cm for the placebo/early induction group (P=0.1), suggesting that treatment preferentially benefited the shortest girls.
        Table 3 also includes the results for maximum height, based on the 92 girls still in the trial. The oxandrolone effect of +4.3 cm (P=0.002) was similar to that for final height (+4.6 cm), and the late induction effect of +2.4 cm (P=0.2) was appreciably smaller than the +3.8 cm for final height. The age of attainment of final height was similar for oxandrolone and placebo (16.2 v 16.7 years; P=0.1) and later, by design, for late versus early induction (16.9 v 16.1 years; P=0.009).
      
      
        SITAR analysis of height curves
        We applied the SITAR analysis to the 105 participants with at least one height measurement (one girl in the control group withdrew immediately after randomisation 1). Figure 2 shows individual height curves unadjusted (top panel) and SITAR adjusted with the summary curve (bottom panel). The curves are labelled according to randomisation 1, and the oxandrolone curves tend to be above and to the left of the placebo curves.
         Fig 2 Individual height growth curves according to randomisation 1: unadjusted (top) and SITAR adjusted (bottom)
        The SITAR adjustment process estimated the size, tempo, and velocity parameters for each participant, which when applied to their curves made them all very similar, with a residual standard deviation of 0.6 mm around the summary curve (fig 2, bottom panel). Comparison of the mean values of the parameters by trial arm showed differences in size (oxandrolone v placebo +2.6 cm; P=0.02) but not tempo (−0.3 years; P=0.1), and the mean velocity was dramatically greater for oxandrolone (difference +23%, SE 4%; P&lt;0.001). This indicated that the developmental age scale in the oxandrolone arm was foreshortened by 23%, increasing the velocity and making the oxandrolone curve correspondingly steeper than the placebo curve, although the age of final height was no earlier. This effect is seen in figure 3 (top panel), which shows SITAR summary curves calculated separately for oxandrolone and placebo. The two curves cross at 10 years, and height velocity is consistently greater in the oxandrolone arm.
         Fig 3 SITAR fitted summary height curves by trial arm for randomisation 1 (top) and randomisation 2 (bottom)
        Figure 3 (bottom panel) shows the corresponding comparison of summary height curves for randomisation 2, late versus early induction. The differences here were smaller, the curves diverging only after 14 years; the late versus early comparisons for size (+2.2 cm) and velocity (−9%) were statistically insignificant (P&gt;0.1), whereas tempo was slightly delayed in the late induction arm (+0.4 years; P=0.06).
      
      
        Adverse events
        Between 1999 and 2009, 197 adverse events were reported; none of them were suspected to be unexpected serious adverse reactions. Ten were classified as serious adverse events, as they involved admission to hospital for procedures including appendicectomy and ear, nose, and throat surgery (for example, grommet (ventilation tube) insertion). Four adverse events could have been related to oxandrolone or ethinylestradiol: acne in a 15 year old (all study drugs were continued, and randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 14 years); persistent hypertension in a 13 year old (oxandrolone/placebo was stopped and antihypertensive treatment started, blood pressure normalised, and oxandrolone/placebo treatment was restarted; the randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 12 years); abnormal liver function in a 16 year old (the participant was at near final height and elected to stop growth promoting treatment; randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 14 years); and episodic “hot flushes” in a 15 year old (all study drugs were continued; randomisation was later revealed as placebo and pubertal induction at 14 years). No virilisation was reported; in particular, no voice deepening or clitoromegaly was noted.
      
    
    
      Discussion
      This randomised controlled trial of growth promoting treatment in Turner’s syndrome showed a clear benefit to final height of oxandrolone treatment and of introducing ethinylestradiol for pubertal induction at age 14 rather than 12 years.
      
        Comparison with other studies
        This positive effect of oxandrolone on final height compares favourably with previous studies.5 6 11 12 Early studies using high doses of oxandrolone had to reduce or stop treatment after reports of virilisation,6 12 and others showed little or no effect of oxandrolone.13 14 However, they were retrospective in design and varied in treatment protocol. In contrast, the UK Turner Study used a prospective placebo controlled design, with consistent doses of oxandrolone throughout. A recent Dutch trial comparing growth hormone with two doses of oxandrolone (0.03 and 0.06 mg/kg/day) reported that the lower dose significantly increased adult “height gain” compared with placebo, whereas the higher dose did not.15 In contrast, the final height in both oxandrolone groups was only approximately 1 cm greater than placebo (156.7 cm and 156.5 cm versus 155.6 cm). The more favourable outcome in the UK study could be related to earlier age at starting growth hormone therapy (6.4 v ~9 years) and also to the lower doses of oxandrolone given in the UK study (0.05 mg/kg/day, maximum 2.5 mg daily) compared with the 0.06 mg/kg/day arm of the Dutch study.
        No adverse events directly attributable to oxandrolone were reported in the UK Turner Study; in particular, no virilisation was reported. Although oxandrolone could have contributed to the cases of acne, hypertension, and abnormal liver function, causality cannot be assumed as these are commonly seen in Turner’s syndrome.25 26 By contrast, the Dutch study reported virilisation in 15/36 girls receiving 0.06 mg/kg/day, which was severe enough for treatment to be discontinued in seven. However, patients receiving placebo also reported virilisation, and how these events were assessed is unclear.15 Furthermore, the maximum daily dose of 2.5 mg used in the UK study irrespective of body weight could account for the absence of reported virilisation.
        The UK Turner Study has also shown a positive effect on final height of introducing ethinylestradiol at age 14 rather than 12 years, consistent with the effect of oestrogen on epiphyseal fusion and supporting previous published associations between delayed pubertal induction and increased height.6 13 18 Since 1999, however, concern has been expressed about the potential cardiovascular, skeletal, reproductive, and psychological consequences of prolonged oestrogen deficiency.19 27 28 29 The finding that oxandrolone allows timely pubertal induction is thus attractive and in keeping with other work.30 31 32 33 34 This study shows that oxandrolone increases height velocity throughout the growing period yet does not materially advance the age of final height.
        However, whereas both oxandrolone and late induction have been shown to increase final height, the two effects were not additive, so that giving either is beneficial but giving both is no better. One possible explanation for this is that there is a “ceiling” for the extra height available from growth promoting strategies in Turner’s syndrome.
        The subset of participants who were randomised twice and received oxandrolone had a larger “gain” in final height than did those who did not need any oestrogen treatment, whether they received oxandrolone or not. The numbers were too small to allow more detailed analysis, but we speculate that the girls who showed spontaneous puberty would have fused their epiphyses earlier than the other girls, which may have resulted in a less favourable final height.
      
      
        Strengths and limitations of study
        This randomised controlled trial has examined a large cohort of patients treated systematically over a 10 year period. Treatment has been well tolerated, such that dropout rates were low (14/106) and the mean final height for the group to date (151.8 cm) is well above the target of 150 cm for girls with Turner’s syndrome treated with growth hormone.6 35 36
        The number of girls who had completed the study and achieved final height at the time of analysis (n=82) fell short of the target sample size of 100. Even when the remaining girls complete the study, the number evaluable at final height will still only be 92. Despite this, however, the group of 82 girls has been sufficient to show positive effects of oxandrolone and delayed pubertal induction, and the addition of the 10 girls yet to complete is unlikely to materially alter the outcome. However, the failure to achieve the target sample size may have limited the ability to detect an interaction between the two randomisations.
        Unfortunately, the break in production of oxandrolone 2.5 mg tablets twice led to deviations from the protocol. Placebo tablets were unavailable for other oxandrolone preparations, and eventually the difficulties in supply led to the early termination of the treatment arm. Therefore, the results may underestimate the true effect of oxandrolone. Even so, they make a strong case for reintroduction of oxandrolone manufacture in Europe or, failing that, affordable importation, as costs of supplies from elsewhere are prohibitive.
        Girls with mosaic Turner’s karyotypes were included in the study. With a larger sample size, the effect of different karyotypes, with varying haploinsufficiency of the SHOX region, on height outcome could be examined. However, the group sizes of those who were randomised twice and attained final height were too small to allow further breakdown by karyotype.
        A measure of bone mineral density was not included in the study protocol and would have provided valuable information. Although its value is now recognised in this patient group, the necessary scanning equipment was not routinely available at all participating centres when the study started.
      
      
        Conclusions and policy implications
        Oxandrolone has a positive effect on final height, as has inducing puberty at age 14 rather than 12 years. However, doing both offers no added benefit. We recommend, therefore, that when growth promotion is being considered in girls with Turner’s syndrome, families are offered oxandrolone as an alternative to late pubertal induction.
        
          
            What is already known on this topic
            
              
                Growth hormone treatment improves growth and stature in girls with Turner’s syndrome
              
              
                However, the adjunctive use of the anabolic steroid oxandrolone remains controversial, with inconsistent reports of effect on growth and virilising side effects
              
              
                Most girls with Turner’s syndrome need oestrogen therapy for pubertal induction, but the optimal age at which to begin treatment and its subsequent effect on growth have yet to be established
              
            
          
          
            What this study adds
            
              
                A large cohort of girls with Turner’s syndrome has been treated systematically over a 10 year period in this randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial
              
              
                Oxandrolone improved final height, as did delaying pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol from age 12 to 14 years, but doing both offered no added benefit
              
            
          
        
      
    
  

Back matter

      
        
          We gratefully acknowledge the enduring support of the participants and their families over the past decade and their willingness to relinquish control over treatment decision making.
        
        
          Contributors: PB, TJC, MDCD, DBD, and PCH were responsible for designing the study. PB, SC, MDCD, EJG, and WP carried out the study. TJC, MDCD, EJG, and RJP analysed the data. TJC, MDCD, DBD, EJG, PCH, and RJP prepared the manuscript. MDCD is the guarantor.
        
        
          Funding: Funding was provided by the Scottish Executive Chief Scientist Office (1999-2004) (K/MRS/50/C2713) and thereafter by the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes, with a contribution to funding of pharmacy staff from the Child Growth Foundation
        
        
          Competing interests: All authors have completed the Unified Competing Interest form at www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: financial support from the Scottish Executive Chief Scientist Office (1999-2004), the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes (2004-2011) and the Child Growth Foundation for the submitted work (MDCD, EJG, SC); travel expenses to attend an international meeting and a departmental honorarium for presenting preliminary results at a specialist nurse workshop (EJG); travel expenses from the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes to attend study Steering Group meetings (MDCD, EJG); royalties from endocrine textbook, consultancy fees for medicolegal reports, and lecture fees from endocrine symposia (MDCD); board membership of Medtronic Diabetes and payment for expert testimony from the MHRA (PH); no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.
        
        
          Ethical approval: The study was approved by the Scotland A Research Ethics Committee (formerly Multi-centre Research Ethics Committee for Scotland) (reference 98/0/92) and by local research ethics committees at participating centres, and written informed consent was obtained. A doctor/dentist exemption (DDX) certificate was obtained and later converted to a clinical trials authorisation (CTA reference 22931/0014/001) by the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency (MHRA).
        
        
          Data sharing: No additional data available.
        
        
          Steering group (British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials/Audit Group): David Dunger (chair), Cambridge; Assunta Albanese (from March 2008), London; Tim Cole, London; John Gregory (from March 2008), Cardiff; Catherine Hall (May 2005 to February 2009), Manchester; Peter Hindmarsh, London; Chris Kelnar, Edinburgh; Jeremy Kirk (until October 2008), Birmingham; Justin Warner (from October 2008), Cardiff. Co-opted members: Malcolm Donaldson, Glasgow; Tim Cheetham, Newcastle.
        
        
          Data and Safety Monitoring Group: Forrester Cockburn, Glasgow; Michael Preece, London; Vincent Yeung, London (1999-2004). The study statistician, Tim Cole, London, also attended meetings.
        
        
          Participating investigators and centres (including medical, nursing, research, secretarial, and pharmacy staff): Peter Smail and Amalia Mayo (Royal Aberdeen Children’s Hospital); Dennis Carson (Royal Belfast Hospital for Sick Children); Jeremy Kirk (Birmingham Children’s Hospital); Stephen Rose (Birmingham Heartlands Hospital); Elizabeth Crowne and Christine Burren (Bristol Royal Hospital for Sick Children); David Dunger, Ieuan Hughes, and Carlo Acerini (Addenbrooke’s Hospital, Cambridge); John Gregory and Justin Warner (University Hospital of Wales, Cardiff); Christine Burren, Atanu Dutta, Assunta Albanese, and Aileen Alston (Queen Mary’s Hospital for Children, Carshalton); Tracy Tinklin (Derbyshire Children’s Hospital); Stephen Greene (Ninewells Hospital, Dundee); Chris Kelnar and Louise Bath (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Edinburgh); Paul Williams and Tony Hulse (Medway Maritime Hospital, Gillingham); Malcolm Donaldson (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Glasgow); Mehul Dattani and Caroline Brain (Great Ormond Street Children’s Hospital, London); Martin Becker (Hinchingbrooke Hospital, Huntingdon); Gary Butler, Sabah Alvi, and Talat Mushtaq (Leeds General Infirmary); Peter Clayton and Catherine Hall (Manchester Children’s Hospital); Mohammed Kibirige and Ginny Birrell (James Cook University Hospital, Middlesbrough); Philip Latham (Milton Keynes General Hospital); Tim Cheetham and Debbie Matthews (Royal Victoria Infirmary, Newcastle-upon-Tyne); Jeremy Allgrove (Newham General Infirmary); John Barton (Royal Gwent Hospital, Newport); Derek Johnston, Tabitha Randell, and Louise Denvir (Queen’s Medical Centre, Nottingham); Vipan Datta and Melanie Kershaw (George Eliot Hospital, Nuneaton); Julie Edge, Fiona Ryan, and Justin Warner (John Radcliffe Hospital, Oxford); Joanna Walker (St Mary’s Hospital, Portsmouth); Andrew Boon, Nicholas Mann, and Gary Butler (Royal Berkshire Hospital, Reading); Peter Stutchfield (Glan Clwyd Hospital, Rhyl); Martin Savage and Jeremy Allgrove (Royal London Hospital); Jerry Wales and Neil Wright (Sheffield Children’s Hospital); Peter Betts and Justin Davies (Southampton General Hospital); John Schulga (Stirling Royal Infirmary); Janet King (Great Western Hospital, Swindon); Heather Stirling (Walsgrave Hospital); Kausik Banerjee, Paramita Cifelli, and Simon Whitmarsh (Whipps Cross Hospital); Janet Anderson (New Cross Hospital, Wolverhampton).
        
        
          Bone age interpretation: Wendy Paterson, Glasgow.
        
        
          Centralised pharmacy services: Sarah Casey and James Wallace, Glasgow.
        
      
    

      Cite this as: BMJ 2011;342:d1980</text>
    <sentence charOffset="0-5" id="S1">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Title</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6-149" id="S2" selection="1a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Effect of oxandrolone and timing of pubertal induction on final height in Turner’s syndrome: randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="150-158" id="S3">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Abstract</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="168-344" id="S4" selection="1b,2b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Objective To examine the effect of oxandrolone and the timing of pubertal induction on final height in girls with Turner’s syndrome receiving a standard dose of growth hormone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="353-411" id="S5" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Design Randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="420-484" id="S6" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Setting 36 paediatric endocrinology departments in UK hospitals.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="493-628" id="S7" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Participants Girls with Turner’s syndrome aged 7-13 years at recruitment, receiving recombinant growth hormone therapy (10 mg/m2/week).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="637-763" id="S8" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Interventions Participants were randomised to oxandrolone (0.05 mg/kg/day, maximum 2.5 mg/day) or placebo from 9 years of age.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="764-1083" id="S9" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Those with evidence of ovarian failure at 12 years were further randomised to oral ethinylestradiol (year 1, 2 µg daily; year 2, 4 μg daily; year 3, 4 months each of 6, 8, and 10 μg daily) or placebo; participants who received placebo and those recruited after the age of 12.25 years started ethinylestradiol at age 14.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1092-1126" id="S10" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Main outcome measure Final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1135-1227" id="S11" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Results 106 participants were recruited, of whom 14 withdrew and 82/92 reached final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1228-1465" id="S12" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Both oxandrolone and late pubertal induction increased final height: by 4.6 (95% confidence interval 1.9 to 7.2) cm (P=0.001, n=82) for oxandrolone and 3.8 (0.0 to 7.5) cm (P=0.05, n=48) for late pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1466-1730" id="S13" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the 48 children who were randomised twice, the effects on final height (compared with placebo and early induction of puberty) of oxandrolone alone, late induction alone, and oxandrolone plus late induction were similar, averaging 7.1 (3.4 to 10.8) cm (P&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1731-1770" id="S14" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">No cases of virilisation were reported.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1779-1970" id="S15" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Conclusion Oxandrolone had a positive effect on final height in girls with Turner’s syndrome treated with growth hormone, as did late pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol at age 14 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1971-2044" id="S16" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, these effects were not additive, so using both had no advantage.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2045-2180" id="S17" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oxandrolone could, therefore, be offered as an alternative to late pubertal induction for increasing final height in Turner’s syndrome.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2189-2249" id="S18" selection="23">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Trial registration Current Controlled Trials ISRCTN50343149.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2270-2282" id="S19">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Introduction</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2289-2419" id="S20" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Turner’s syndrome can be defined as absence or abnormality of the second X chromosome in a major cell line in a phenotypic female.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2420-2515" id="S21" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The phenotype is highly variable, but short stature and gonadal dysgenesis are usually present.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2516-2754" id="S22" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Short stature in Turner’s syndrome relates to impairment of each phase of the infancy-childhood-puberty model of growth,1 and it results in a mean untreated final height approximately 21 cm below that of the unaffected female population.2</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2755-2893" id="S23" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The mainstay of treatment for short stature is recombinant growth hormone, available since 1985 and licensed for use in Turner’s syndrome.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2894-3032" id="S24" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Studies have shown its efficacy in improving height velocity and final height, although individual outcomes vary markedly.3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3039-3137" id="S25" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The adjunctive use in Turner’s syndrome of the anabolic steroid oxandrolone remains controversial.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3138-3309" id="S26" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">When given in combination with growth hormone treatment, some studies have reported improved final height,6 11 12 whereas others have reported little or no effect.13 14 15</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3310-3473" id="S27" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The high doses used in early studies were associated with virilisation,6 12 14 and even low doses, as reported in a recent Dutch publication, may be problematic.15</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3474-3563" id="S28" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">These potential adverse effects must be balanced against potential improvement in growth.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3570-3679" id="S29" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Most girls with Turner’s syndrome need oestrogen therapy during adolescence to induce pubertal development.16</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3680-3972" id="S30" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the optimal age at which to begin remains controversial; some people advocate a delay to extend the growth period and increase final height,5 6 17 18 whereas others have highlighted psychological problems of delaying pubertal development, suggesting that the benefits are marginal.19</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3973-4191" id="S31" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes recognised the uncertainties relating to the use of oxandrolone and timing of pubertal induction and set up the UK Turner Study in 1999 to investigate them.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4208-4215" id="S32">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Methods</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4231-4243" id="S33" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Participants</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4252-4416" id="S34" selection="4b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Members of the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes recruited patients from participating paediatric endocrinology departments in UK hospitals.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4417-4769" id="S35" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Inclusion criteria for participation of patients were karyotype confirmed Turner’s syndrome (all karyotypes were eligible, including mosaic), age 7-13 years, no previous growth hormone treatment or previous treatment in the range 8.3-11.7 mg/m2/week in five to seven injections a week, no previous oxandrolone and oestrogen therapy, and open epiphyses.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4770-4922" id="S36" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Exclusion criteria were major systemic illness that might affect growth and social or psychological difficulties likely to seriously impair concordance.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4945-4957" id="S37" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Study design</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4966-5104" id="S38" selection="3a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We devised a double blind, placebo controlled, randomised controlled trial, including two randomisations in a two by two factorial design.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5105-5166" id="S39" selection="3a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 1 shows the flow chart of the design and participants.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5167-5366" id="S40" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A steering committee (British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials/Audit Group) supervised the study, and an independent data and safety monitoring group was established.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5367-5423" id="S41" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All participants’ parents gave written informed consent.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5433-5546" id="S42" selection="3a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Fig 1 Flow chart of participation in UK Turner Study according to treatment groups, completions, and withdrawals.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5547-5653" id="S43" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">*Withdrawn before 12 years of age (that is, randomised only at randomisation 1 to oxandrolone or placebo).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5654-5751" id="S44" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">†Aged ≥12.25 years at recruitment; oestrogen treatment started at 14 years with no randomisation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5752-5904" id="S45" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">‡Withdrawn after 12 years of age (that is, randomised at randomisation 1 to oxandrolone or placebo and at randomisation 2 if oestrogen treatment needed)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5927-5952" id="S46" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Randomisation and masking</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5961-6141" id="S47" selection="8b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials Unit (Cambridge, UK) used minimisation by weighted randomisation for the study’s two randomisations.20</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6142-6361" id="S48" selection="10,5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Randomisation 1, to oxandrolone or placebo, took place at age 9 years (or at enrolment, if older) and was balanced for enrolling centre, quarter of mid-parental height, and previous exposure to growth hormone treatment.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6362-6674" id="S49" selection="10,5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Randomisation 2 took place at age 12 years in girls with ovarian failure (basal serum follicle stimulating hormone concentration &gt;10 U/L), with additional minimisation for randomisation 1, to begin oral ethinylestradiol or placebo at 12 years; the placebo group subsequently started ethinylestradiol at 14 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6675-6910" id="S50" selection="10">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Girls with a follicle stimulating hormone concentration below 10U/L and a karyotype associated with preservation of ovarian function (45,X/46,XX and 45,X/47,XXX21) (the spontaneous puberty group) were not randomised at randomisation 2.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6911-7116" id="S51" selection="10">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Girls with other karyotypes were tested for concentrations of gonadotrophin releasing hormone and were randomised at randomisation 2 if the peak follicle stimulating hormone concentration was above 30 U/L.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7117-7254" id="S52" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Participants enrolled after the age of 12.25 years and without spontaneous puberty (the late group) started ethinylestradiol at 14 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7277-7286" id="S53" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Treatment</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7295-7418" id="S54" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All participants received the growth hormone preparation of their choice at 10 mg/m2/week in daily subcutaneous injections.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7419-7521" id="S55" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oral oxandrolone (SPA, Milan, Italy) was given at 0.05 mg/kg/day, with a maximum daily dose of 2.5 mg.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7522-7704" id="S56" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oral ethinylestradiol (UCB Pharma, Slough, UK) was given daily as follows, regardless of the age at starting: year 1, 2 μg; year 2, 4 μg; year 3, four months each of 6, 8, and 10 μg.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7705-7894" id="S57" selection="5,10">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The code for randomisation 2 was broken at 15 years to allow introduction of progesterone therapy: oral norethisterone (CP Pharmaceuticals, Wrexham, UK) 5 mg daily for five days each month.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7903-7990" id="S58" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Treatment with growth hormone and oxandrolone continued until final height was reached.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7991-8099" id="S59" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oestrogen/progesterone therapy continued at an adult replacement dose once pubertal induction was completed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8108-8358" id="S60" selection="11b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">White, uncoated, flat bevelled edge placebo tablets (7 and 5 mm in diameter) (Essential Nutrition, Brough, UK) were specially manufactured to match the size, weight, and appearance of oxandrolone 2.5 mg and ethinylestradiol 2 µg tablets respectively.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8359-8681" id="S61" selection="11a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study’s central pharmacy (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Glasgow, UK) supplied all tablets in a double blind, placebo controlled fashion; only staff at the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials Unit and the central distributing pharmacy were not blinded to treatment allocations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8704-8724" id="S62" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oxandrolone supplies</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8733-8974" id="S63" selection="3b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In 2004 and 2008, the sole European manufacturer of oxandrolone 2.5 mg ceased production, resulting in 34 participants in 2004 and 11 in 2008 temporarily suspending active oxandrolone treatment (mean duration: 2004, 52 days; 2008, 163 days).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8975-9124" id="S64" selection="3b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In 2008, the decision was taken to terminate the treatment arm forthwith, resulting in eight participants stopping oxandrolone treatment prematurely.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9147-9163" id="S65" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Study procedures</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9172-9358" id="S66" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At clinic visits every four to six months, height was measured with a Harpenden stadiometer to the last completed 1 mm and converted to an SD score by using the British 1990 reference.22</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9359-9526" id="S67" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Radiographs of the left wrist were obtained annually, and a single observer (WFP) analysed them for bone age estimation according to the Tanner Whitehouse II method.23</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9527-9614" id="S68" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Biochemical analyses followed local protocols, and the results were reported centrally.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9623-9802" id="S69" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Standardised pharmacovigilance procedures were followed, with recording of adverse events or reactions at each visit and subsequent review by the Data and Safety Monitoring Group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9803-9923" id="S70" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data collection ceased if participants withdrew consent, although we included previously collected data in the analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9946-9965" id="S71" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Statistical methods</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9974-10092" id="S72" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary outcome was final height, defined as height velocity less than 1 cm/year and bone age at least 15.5 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10093-10290" id="S73" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Secondary outcomes were maximum height (that is, the most recently available height), age of attaining final height, and the three summary growth parameters from the SITAR analysis described below.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10299-10498" id="S74" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Assuming a standard deviation of 5 cm, we needed 50 girls in each group to detect a difference between groups in mean final height of 2.8 cm with 80% power at 5% significance—a total of 100 patients.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10499-10601" id="S75" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study was not formally powered to detect a significant interaction between the two randomisations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10602-10707" id="S76" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the event, more than 100 patients were recruited, but fewer than 100 were followed up to final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10716-10807" id="S77" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We estimated the effects of the two randomisations separately by using multiple regression.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10808-10936" id="S78" selection="12b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We also adjusted randomisation 2 (timing of pubertal induction) for randomisation 1 (oxandrolone) and tested for an interaction.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10945-11077" id="S79" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In addition, we applied SITAR (superimposition by translation and rotation), a novel method of growth curve analysis, to the data.24</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11078-11232" id="S80" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">SITAR transforms individual growth curves so that they become essentially the same as each other and, when superimposed, define the average summary curve.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11233-11510" id="S81" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">To achieve this, each individual curve is suitably altered in three distinct ways: the curve is shifted up/down (a measure of the child’s size in cm) and left/right (a measure of growth tempo in years), and the age axis is stretched/squashed (a measure of percentage velocity).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11511-11647" id="S82" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Size, tempo, and velocity are thus participant specific random effects summarising how each girl’s curve differs from the average curve.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11648-11757" id="S83" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The effects of the randomisations can be explored by comparing the values of the random effects by trial arm.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11758-11829" id="S84" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Equally, separate summary curves can be constructed for each trial arm.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11853-11860" id="S85">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Results</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11867-12091" id="S86" selection="14a,13b,13a,16">
        <text xml:space="preserve">One hundred and six girls with Turner’s syndrome were recruited from 36 UK hospitals between 1999 and 2003, of whom 14 withdrew (four of them because of early organisational errors), leaving 92 to complete the study (fig 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12092-12467" id="S87" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The breakdown of karyotypes was 45,X (39), 45,X/46,XX (18), 45,X/46,XrX (9), complex mosaics containing three or more cell lines (8), 45,X/46,XiX (7), 45,X/45,XY (7), 46,XX including a structural abnormality of second X (7), 45,X/46,XY including a structural abnormality of Y (3), 45,X/46,XX including a structural abnormality of second X (3), 45,X/47,XXX (2), and other (3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12474-12679" id="S88" selection="13a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All 106 participants were randomised at or after 9 years of age to oxandrolone or placebo (randomisation 1), and 60 were also randomised at 12 years to early or late induction of puberty (randomisation 2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12680-12848" id="S89" selection="13a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Of the 46 girls not randomised at 12 years, 21 enrolled after 12 years (the late group), 18 had spontaneous puberty, and seven had withdrawn before the age of 12 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12864-12888" id="S90" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Final and maximum height</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12897-13013" id="S91" selection="15,17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 1 shows participants’ characteristics at enrolment, at maximum height, and at final height by treatment group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13014-13141" id="S92" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the time of writing, 82 participants had attained a mean final height of 151.8 (SD 6.4) cm, and 10 others continued growing.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13142-13243" id="S93" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 2 shows details of final height and maximum height according to the study’s two randomisations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13252-13370" id="S94" selection="15,17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 1  Characteristics of participants at enrolment, maximum height, and final height, according to treatment group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13371-13415" id="S95" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Values are mean (SD) unless stated otherwise</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13424-13612" id="S96" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 2  Final height and maximum height data for participants randomised twice, according to randomisation 1 (oxandrolone/placebo) and randomisation 2 (pubertal induction at 14/12 years).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13613-13633" id="S97" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Values are mean (SD)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13642-13852" id="S98" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">By twice randomised group, the mean final heights were placebo/early induction 147.0 cm, placebo/late induction 153.1 cm, oxandrolone/early induction 154.4 cm, and oxandrolone/late induction 155.1 cm (table 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13853-13914" id="S99" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 3 summarises the results of the randomised comparisons.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13915-14059" id="S100" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">For randomisation 1, final height was significantly greater with oxandrolone than placebo (4.6 cm, 95% confidence interval 1.9 to 7.2; P=0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14060-14213" id="S101" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Similarly, for randomisation 2, final height was significantly greater with pubertal induction at 14 years than at 12 years (3.8 cm, 0.0 to 7.5; P=0.05).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14222-14348" id="S102" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 3  Effects of two randomisations, their interaction, and their combination, on mean final height and mean maximum height</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14357-14439" id="S103" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the positive effects of oxandrolone and late induction were not additive.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14440-14701" id="S104" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Among girls previously randomised to oxandrolone, the effect of late induction compared with early induction was clinically insignificant (+0.7 cm); in the placebo group, however, late induction added 6.2 cm compared with early induction (table 3, interaction).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14702-14855" id="S105" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The two treatments together were thus no more effective than either one alone, as shown by the substantial and close to significant negative interaction.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14856-15241" id="S106" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The mean effect on final height of oxandrolone, late induction of puberty, or both compared with placebo and early induction was +7.1 cm (that is, the mean final height in the combined oxandrolone/early, oxandrolone/late, and placebo/late groups compared with the placebo/early group), which is appreciably larger than the effects for either randomisation alone (table 3, combination).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15242-15471" id="S107" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This was because the randomisation analyses compared intervention and control groups in which half of each control group had received an effective intervention from the other randomisation, thus reducing the apparent effect size.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15472-15675" id="S108" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The standard deviation for the combined group was 5.1 cm, rather less than the 7.4 cm for the placebo/early induction group (P=0.1), suggesting that treatment preferentially benefited the shortest girls.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15684-15779" id="S109" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 3 also includes the results for maximum height, based on the 92 girls still in the trial.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15780-15979" id="S110" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The oxandrolone effect of +4.3 cm (P=0.002) was similar to that for final height (+4.6 cm), and the late induction effect of +2.4 cm (P=0.2) was appreciably smaller than the +3.8 cm for final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15980-16168" id="S111" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The age of attainment of final height was similar for oxandrolone and placebo (16.2 v 16.7 years; P=0.1) and later, by design, for late versus early induction (16.9 v 16.1 years; P=0.009).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16191-16222" id="S112" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">SITAR analysis of height curves</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16231-16397" id="S113" selection="13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We applied the SITAR analysis to the 105 participants with at least one height measurement (one girl in the control group withdrew immediately after randomisation 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16398-16518" id="S114" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 2 shows individual height curves unadjusted (top panel) and SITAR adjusted with the summary curve (bottom panel).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16519-16655" id="S115" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The curves are labelled according to randomisation 1, and the oxandrolone curves tend to be above and to the left of the placebo curves.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16665-16777" id="S116" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Fig 2 Individual height growth curves according to randomisation 1: unadjusted (top) and SITAR adjusted (bottom)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16786-17043" id="S117" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The SITAR adjustment process estimated the size, tempo, and velocity parameters for each participant, which when applied to their curves made them all very similar, with a residual standard deviation of 0.6 mm around the summary curve (fig 2, bottom panel).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17044-17304" id="S118" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Comparison of the mean values of the parameters by trial arm showed differences in size (oxandrolone v placebo +2.6 cm; P=0.02) but not tempo (−0.3 years; P=0.1), and the mean velocity was dramatically greater for oxandrolone (difference +23%, SE 4%; P&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17305-17555" id="S119" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This indicated that the developmental age scale in the oxandrolone arm was foreshortened by 23%, increasing the velocity and making the oxandrolone curve correspondingly steeper than the placebo curve, although the age of final height was no earlier.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17556-17684" id="S120" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This effect is seen in figure 3 (top panel), which shows SITAR summary curves calculated separately for oxandrolone and placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17685-17786" id="S121" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The two curves cross at 10 years, and height velocity is consistently greater in the oxandrolone arm.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17796-17904" id="S122" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Fig 3 SITAR fitted summary height curves by trial arm for randomisation 1 (top) and randomisation 2 (bottom)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17913-18046" id="S123" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 3 (bottom panel) shows the corresponding comparison of summary height curves for randomisation 2, late versus early induction.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18047-18320" id="S124" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The differences here were smaller, the curves diverging only after 14 years; the late versus early comparisons for size (+2.2 cm) and velocity (−9%) were statistically insignificant (P&gt;0.1), whereas tempo was slightly delayed in the late induction arm (+0.4 years; P=0.06).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18343-18357" id="S125" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Adverse events</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18366-18494" id="S126" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Between 1999 and 2009, 197 adverse events were reported; none of them were suspected to be unexpected serious adverse reactions.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18495-18707" id="S127" selection="19">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Ten were classified as serious adverse events, as they involved admission to hospital for procedures including appendicectomy and ear, nose, and throat surgery (for example, grommet (ventilation tube) insertion).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18708-19584" id="S128" selection="19">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Four adverse events could have been related to oxandrolone or ethinylestradiol: acne in a 15 year old (all study drugs were continued, and randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 14 years); persistent hypertension in a 13 year old (oxandrolone/placebo was stopped and antihypertensive treatment started, blood pressure normalised, and oxandrolone/placebo treatment was restarted; the randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 12 years); abnormal liver function in a 16 year old (the participant was at near final height and elected to stop growth promoting treatment; randomisation was later revealed as oxandrolone and pubertal induction at 14 years); and episodic “hot flushes” in a 15 year old (all study drugs were continued; randomisation was later revealed as placebo and pubertal induction at 14 years).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19585-19676" id="S129" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">No virilisation was reported; in particular, no voice deepening or clitoromegaly was noted.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19700-19710" id="S130">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Discussion</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19717-19955" id="S131" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This randomised controlled trial of growth promoting treatment in Turner’s syndrome showed a clear benefit to final height of oxandrolone treatment and of introducing ethinylestradiol for pubertal induction at age 14 rather than 12 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19971-20000" id="S132" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Comparison with other studies</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20009-20112" id="S133" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This positive effect of oxandrolone on final height compares favourably with previous studies.5 6 11 12</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20113-20284" id="S134" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Early studies using high doses of oxandrolone had to reduce or stop treatment after reports of virilisation,6 12 and others showed little or no effect of oxandrolone.13 14</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20285-20361" id="S135" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, they were retrospective in design and varied in treatment protocol.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20362-20489" id="S136" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In contrast, the UK Turner Study used a prospective placebo controlled design, with consistent doses of oxandrolone throughout.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20490-20722" id="S137" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A recent Dutch trial comparing growth hormone with two doses of oxandrolone (0.03 and 0.06 mg/kg/day) reported that the lower dose significantly increased adult “height gain” compared with placebo, whereas the higher dose did not.15</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20723-20869" id="S138" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In contrast, the final height in both oxandrolone groups was only approximately 1 cm greater than placebo (156.7 cm and 156.5 cm versus 155.6 cm).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20870-21158" id="S139" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The more favourable outcome in the UK study could be related to earlier age at starting growth hormone therapy (6.4 v ~9 years) and also to the lower doses of oxandrolone given in the UK study (0.05 mg/kg/day, maximum 2.5 mg daily) compared with the 0.06 mg/kg/day arm of the Dutch study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21167-21304" id="S140" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">No adverse events directly attributable to oxandrolone were reported in the UK Turner Study; in particular, no virilisation was reported.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21305-21495" id="S141" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Although oxandrolone could have contributed to the cases of acne, hypertension, and abnormal liver function, causality cannot be assumed as these are commonly seen in Turner’s syndrome.25 26</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21496-21654" id="S142" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">By contrast, the Dutch study reported virilisation in 15/36 girls receiving 0.06 mg/kg/day, which was severe enough for treatment to be discontinued in seven.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21655-21767" id="S143" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, patients receiving placebo also reported virilisation, and how these events were assessed is unclear.15</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21768-21918" id="S144" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Furthermore, the maximum daily dose of 2.5 mg used in the UK study irrespective of body weight could account for the absence of reported virilisation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21927-22231" id="S145" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The UK Turner Study has also shown a positive effect on final height of introducing ethinylestradiol at age 14 rather than 12 years, consistent with the effect of oestrogen on epiphyseal fusion and supporting previous published associations between delayed pubertal induction and increased height.6 13 18</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22232-22416" id="S146" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Since 1999, however, concern has been expressed about the potential cardiovascular, skeletal, reproductive, and psychological consequences of prolonged oestrogen deficiency.19 27 28 29</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22417-22543" id="S147" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The finding that oxandrolone allows timely pubertal induction is thus attractive and in keeping with other work.30 31 32 33 34</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22544-22690" id="S148" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This study shows that oxandrolone increases height velocity throughout the growing period yet does not materially advance the age of final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22699-22894" id="S149" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, whereas both oxandrolone and late induction have been shown to increase final height, the two effects were not additive, so that giving either is beneficial but giving both is no better.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22895-23043" id="S150" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">One possible explanation for this is that there is a “ceiling” for the extra height available from growth promoting strategies in Turner’s syndrome.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23052-23264" id="S151" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The subset of participants who were randomised twice and received oxandrolone had a larger “gain” in final height than did those who did not need any oestrogen treatment, whether they received oxandrolone or not.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23265-23509" id="S152" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The numbers were too small to allow more detailed analysis, but we speculate that the girls who showed spontaneous puberty would have fused their epiphyses earlier than the other girls, which may have resulted in a less favourable final height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23532-23566" id="S153" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Strengths and limitations of study</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23575-23693" id="S154" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This randomised controlled trial has examined a large cohort of patients treated systematically over a 10 year period.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23694-23933" id="S155" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Treatment has been well tolerated, such that dropout rates were low (14/106) and the mean final height for the group to date (151.8 cm) is well above the target of 150 cm for girls with Turner’s syndrome treated with growth hormone.6 35 36</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23942-24091" id="S156" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The number of girls who had completed the study and achieved final height at the time of analysis (n=82) fell short of the target sample size of 100.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24092-24201" id="S157" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Even when the remaining girls complete the study, the number evaluable at final height will still only be 92.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24202-24432" id="S158" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Despite this, however, the group of 82 girls has been sufficient to show positive effects of oxandrolone and delayed pubertal induction, and the addition of the 10 girls yet to complete is unlikely to materially alter the outcome.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24433-24573" id="S159" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the failure to achieve the target sample size may have limited the ability to detect an interaction between the two randomisations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24582-24693" id="S160" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Unfortunately, the break in production of oxandrolone 2.5 mg tablets twice led to deviations from the protocol.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24694-24855" id="S161" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Placebo tablets were unavailable for other oxandrolone preparations, and eventually the difficulties in supply led to the early termination of the treatment arm.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24856-24928" id="S162" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Therefore, the results may underestimate the true effect of oxandrolone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24929-25112" id="S163" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Even so, they make a strong case for reintroduction of oxandrolone manufacture in Europe or, failing that, affordable importation, as costs of supplies from elsewhere are prohibitive.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25121-25186" id="S164" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Girls with mosaic Turner’s karyotypes were included in the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25187-25338" id="S165" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">With a larger sample size, the effect of different karyotypes, with varying haploinsufficiency of the SHOX region, on height outcome could be examined.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25339-25480" id="S166" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the group sizes of those who were randomised twice and attained final height were too small to allow further breakdown by karyotype.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25489-25607" id="S167" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A measure of bone mineral density was not included in the study protocol and would have provided valuable information.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25608-25781" id="S168" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Although its value is now recognised in this patient group, the necessary scanning equipment was not routinely available at all participating centres when the study started.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25804-25839" id="S169" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Conclusions and policy implications</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25848-25954" id="S170" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oxandrolone has a positive effect on final height, as has inducing puberty at age 14 rather than 12 years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25955-25999" id="S171" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, doing both offers no added benefit.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26000-26183" id="S172" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We recommend, therefore, that when growth promotion is being considered in girls with Turner’s syndrome, families are offered oxandrolone as an alternative to late pubertal induction.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26216-26251" id="S173" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">What is already known on this topic</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26296-26380" id="S174" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Growth hormone treatment improves growth and stature in girls with Turner’s syndrome</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26427-26587" id="S175" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the adjunctive use of the anabolic steroid oxandrolone remains controversial, with inconsistent reports of effect on growth and virilising side effects</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26634-26825" id="S176" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Most girls with Turner’s syndrome need oestrogen therapy for pubertal induction, but the optimal age at which to begin treatment and its subsequent effect on growth have yet to be established</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26888-26908" id="S177" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">What this study adds</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26953-27112" id="S178" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A large cohort of girls with Turner’s syndrome has been treated systematically over a 10 year period in this randomised, double blind, placebo controlled trial</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27159-27315" id="S179" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Oxandrolone improved final height, as did delaying pubertal induction with ethinylestradiol from age 12 to 14 years, but doing both offered no added benefit</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27380-27391" id="S180">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Back matter</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27419-27601" id="S181" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We gratefully acknowledge the enduring support of the participants and their families over the past decade and their willingness to relinquish control over treatment decision making.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27630-27713" id="S182" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Contributors: PB, TJC, MDCD, DBD, and PCH were responsible for designing the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27714-27762" id="S183" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">PB, SC, MDCD, EJG, and WP carried out the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27763-27805" id="S184" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">TJC, MDCD, EJG, and RJP analysed the data.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27806-27864" id="S185" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">TJC, MDCD, DBD, EJG, PCH, and RJP prepared the manuscript.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27865-27887" id="S186" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">MDCD is the guarantor.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27916-28186" id="S187" selection="25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Funding: Funding was provided by the Scottish Executive Chief Scientist Office (1999-2004) (K/MRS/50/C2713) and thereafter by the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes, with a contribution to funding of pharmacy staff from the Child Growth Foundation</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28215-29177" id="S188" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Competing interests: All authors have completed the Unified Competing Interest form at www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: financial support from the Scottish Executive Chief Scientist Office (1999-2004), the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes (2004-2011) and the Child Growth Foundation for the submitted work (MDCD, EJG, SC); travel expenses to attend an international meeting and a departmental honorarium for presenting preliminary results at a specialist nurse workshop (EJG); travel expenses from the British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes to attend study Steering Group meetings (MDCD, EJG); royalties from endocrine textbook, consultancy fees for medicolegal reports, and lecture fees from endocrine symposia (MDCD); board membership of Medtronic Diabetes and payment for expert testimony from the MHRA (PH); no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29206-29482" id="S189" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Ethical approval: The study was approved by the Scotland A Research Ethics Committee (formerly Multi-centre Research Ethics Committee for Scotland) (reference 98/0/92) and by local research ethics committees at participating centres, and written informed consent was obtained.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29483-29693" id="S190" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A doctor/dentist exemption (DDX) certificate was obtained and later converted to a clinical trials authorisation (CTA reference 22931/0014/001) by the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency (MHRA).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29722-29765" id="S191" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data sharing: No additional data available.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29794-30229" id="S192" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Steering group (British Society for Paediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes Clinical Trials/Audit Group): David Dunger (chair), Cambridge; Assunta Albanese (from March 2008), London; Tim Cole, London; John Gregory (from March 2008), Cardiff; Catherine Hall (May 2005 to February 2009), Manchester; Peter Hindmarsh, London; Chris Kelnar, Edinburgh; Jeremy Kirk (until October 2008), Birmingham; Justin Warner (from October 2008), Cardiff.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30230-30300" id="S193" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Co-opted members: Malcolm Donaldson, Glasgow; Tim Cheetham, Newcastle.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30329-30450" id="S194" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data and Safety Monitoring Group: Forrester Cockburn, Glasgow; Michael Preece, London; Vincent Yeung, London (1999-2004).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30451-30516" id="S195" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study statistician, Tim Cole, London, also attended meetings.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30545-32956" id="S196" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Participating investigators and centres (including medical, nursing, research, secretarial, and pharmacy staff): Peter Smail and Amalia Mayo (Royal Aberdeen Children’s Hospital); Dennis Carson (Royal Belfast Hospital for Sick Children); Jeremy Kirk (Birmingham Children’s Hospital); Stephen Rose (Birmingham Heartlands Hospital); Elizabeth Crowne and Christine Burren (Bristol Royal Hospital for Sick Children); David Dunger, Ieuan Hughes, and Carlo Acerini (Addenbrooke’s Hospital, Cambridge); John Gregory and Justin Warner (University Hospital of Wales, Cardiff); Christine Burren, Atanu Dutta, Assunta Albanese, and Aileen Alston (Queen Mary’s Hospital for Children, Carshalton); Tracy Tinklin (Derbyshire Children’s Hospital); Stephen Greene (Ninewells Hospital, Dundee); Chris Kelnar and Louise Bath (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Edinburgh); Paul Williams and Tony Hulse (Medway Maritime Hospital, Gillingham); Malcolm Donaldson (Royal Hospital for Sick Children, Glasgow); Mehul Dattani and Caroline Brain (Great Ormond Street Children’s Hospital, London); Martin Becker (Hinchingbrooke Hospital, Huntingdon); Gary Butler, Sabah Alvi, and Talat Mushtaq (Leeds General Infirmary); Peter Clayton and Catherine Hall (Manchester Children’s Hospital); Mohammed Kibirige and Ginny Birrell (James Cook University Hospital, Middlesbrough); Philip Latham (Milton Keynes General Hospital); Tim Cheetham and Debbie Matthews (Royal Victoria Infirmary, Newcastle-upon-Tyne); Jeremy Allgrove (Newham General Infirmary); John Barton (Royal Gwent Hospital, Newport); Derek Johnston, Tabitha Randell, and Louise Denvir (Queen’s Medical Centre, Nottingham); Vipan Datta and Melanie Kershaw (George Eliot Hospital, Nuneaton); Julie Edge, Fiona Ryan, and Justin Warner (John Radcliffe Hospital, Oxford); Joanna Walker (St Mary’s Hospital, Portsmouth); Andrew Boon, Nicholas Mann, and Gary Butler (Royal Berkshire Hospital, Reading); Peter Stutchfield (Glan Clwyd Hospital, Rhyl); Martin Savage and Jeremy Allgrove (Royal London Hospital); Jerry Wales and Neil Wright (Sheffield Children’s Hospital); Peter Betts and Justin Davies (Southampton General Hospital); John Schulga (Stirling Royal Infirmary); Janet King (Great Western Hospital, Swindon); Heather Stirling (Walsgrave Hospital); Kausik Banerjee, Paramita Cifelli, and Simon Whitmarsh (Whipps Cross Hospital); Janet Anderson (New Cross Hospital, Wolverhampton).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32985-33034" id="S197" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Bone age interpretation: Wendy Paterson, Glasgow.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33063-33133" id="S198" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Centralised pharmacy services: Sarah Casey and James Wallace, Glasgow.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33162-33194" id="S199" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Cite this as: BMJ 2011;342:d1980</text>
    </sentence>
    <section textSpan="0-149" title="Title" titleSpan="0-5"/>
    <section textSpan="150-2257" title="Abstract" titleSpan="150-158"/>
    <section textSpan="2263-4196" title="Introduction" titleSpan="2270-2282"/>
    <section textSpan="4201-11841" title="Methods" titleSpan="4208-4215">
        <section textSpan="4222-4929" title="Participants" titleSpan="4231-4243"/>
        <section textSpan="4936-5911" title="Study design" titleSpan="4945-4957"/>
        <section textSpan="5918-7261" title="Randomisation and masking" titleSpan="5927-5952"/>
        <section textSpan="7268-8688" title="Treatment" titleSpan="7277-7286"/>
        <section textSpan="8695-9131" title="Oxandrolone supplies" titleSpan="8704-8724"/>
        <section textSpan="9138-9930" title="Study procedures" titleSpan="9147-9163"/>
        <section textSpan="9937-11836" title="Statistical methods" titleSpan="9946-9965"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="11846-19688" title="Results" titleSpan="11853-11860">
        <section textSpan="12855-16175" title="Final and maximum height" titleSpan="12864-12888"/>
        <section textSpan="16182-18327" title="SITAR analysis of height curves" titleSpan="16191-16222"/>
        <section textSpan="18334-19683" title="Adverse events" titleSpan="18343-18357"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="19693-27375" title="Discussion" titleSpan="19700-19710">
        <section textSpan="19962-23516" title="Comparison with other studies" titleSpan="19971-20000"/>
        <section textSpan="23523-25788" title="Strengths and limitations of study" titleSpan="23532-23566"/>
        <section textSpan="25795-27370" title="Conclusions and policy implications" titleSpan="25804-25839">
            <section textSpan="26203-26864" title="What is already known on this topic" titleSpan="26216-26251"/>
            <section textSpan="26875-27354" title="What this study adds" titleSpan="26888-26908"/>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="27380-33200" title="Back matter" titleSpan="27380-27391"/>
</document>
