<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<document id="PMC4085478" note="">
    <text xml:space="preserve">Title
First Multicenter Study of Modified Release Phosphatidylcholine “LT-02” in Ulcerative Colitis: A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial in Mesalazine-Refractory Courses
Abstract

        
          OBJECTIVES:
          Phosphatidylcholine is a key component of the mucosal barrier. Treatment with modified release phosphatidylcholine aims to improve the impaired barrier function. The primary objective is to evaluate the efficacy of LT-02, a newly designed modified release phosphatidylcholine formula, in a multicenter setting.
        
        
          METHODS:
          This is a double-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled, superiority study conducted in 24 ambulatory referral centers in Germany, Lithuania, and Romania. A total of 156 patients with an inadequate response to mesalazine, a disease activity score (Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index (SCCAI)) of ≥5, and bloody diarrhea underwent treatment with 0, 0.8, 1.6, or 3.2 g LT-02. The primary end point was defined a priori as changes in SCCAI from baseline to the end of treatment. The primary statistical model was a general linear least-squares model. The study was funded by the sponsor Lipid Therapeutics, Heidelberg, Germany, and registered at http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01011322.
        
        
          RESULTS:
          Baseline characteristics and dropouts were well balanced between all groups. The primary analyses revealed an SCCAI drop of 33.3% in the placebo group (from 9.0 to 6.0 points) compared with 44.3% in the 0.8 g LT-02 (from 8.8 to 4.9, P&gt;0.05) and 40.7% in the 1.6 g groups (from 8.6 to 5.1, P&gt;0.05). The 3.2 g group improved 51.7% from 8.5 to 4.1 (P=0.030 in comparison with placebo). The remission rate was 15% (6/40) in the placebo group compared with 31.4% (11/35) in the highest LT-02 dose group (P=0.089). Mucosal healing was achieved in 32.5% of placebo patients compared with 47.4% of LT-02 patients (P=0.098); the rates for histologic remission were 20% compared with 40.5%, respectively (P=0.016). There were 17 (48.6%) treatment-emergent adverse events in the highest dose group (and 0 serious adverse events (SAEs)) compared with 22 (55%) in the placebo group (4 SAEs).
        
        
          CONCLUSIONS:
          The primary end point analysis showed a statistically significant improvement in disease activity during LT-02 treatment in comparison with placebo. The drug was found to be very safe.
        
       Table A2b Detailed listing of adverse events  Table A2a Categories of adverse events (AEs)  Table A2c Serious adverse events (SAEs)  Table A1 Remission rates over time 






    
      INTRODUCTION
      Ulcerative colitis (UC) is an inflammatory bowel disease that affects the distal colon, potentially spreading over the entire colon. The incidence is 5—20/100,000 in western countries, with a prevalence of 0.02—0.23% (1). First-line pharmacotherapy consists of 5-aminosalicylic acids and/or steroids for acute episodes. Aminosalicylates and thiopurines, but not steroids, should be used for maintenance therapy. Calcineurin and tumor necrosis factor-α antagonists may work in refractory cases, but the effects wear off over time and adverse events can be limiting (2,3,4,5); see also FDA block warning on tumor necrosis factor blockers). Moreover, tumor necrosis factor antibodies are highly cost intensive. Current therapeutic regimens therefore are not always successful. The 10-year cumulative risk of colectomy is ∼9% (6). An unmet medical need for a safe and effective therapy remains.
      Phosphatidylcholine (PC) was found to be an essential protective component of colonic mucus (7,8,9). The novel treatment of modified release PC was based on the observation that specifically patients with UC had a low intrinsic mucus PC content that reduces the hydrophobic barrier function of the intestinal mucus (10,11). Colonic bacteria may then permeate the intestinal mucus barrier, and the consecutive unspecific but aggressive immune responses lead to inflammation and ulceration (12). Moreover, the intrinsic anti-inflammatory property of PC is lacking which, in turn, perpetuates the mucosal damage (13,14). The purpose of modified release PC is to reconstitute the low mucus PC reservoir and to re-establish the mucosal barrier (9,15,16,17). Three previous studies have shown efficacy using a modified release preparation of soy lecithin containing 30% PC (18,19,20). The altered bioavailability of modified release PC aims to release PC in the distal ileum, thereby avoiding early intestinal absorption. The formula was optimized to LT-02, which contains &gt;94% PC concentrated soy lecithin, to allow for regulatory approval.
      The goal of the present trial was to evaluate the clinical efficacy, optimal dose, and safety of LT-02.
    
    
      METHODS
       Figure 1 Study flowchart. Inclusion criteria were as follows: proven mesalazine-refractory ulcerative colitis (European consensus definition (16) with an inadequate response to mesalazine for 6 weeks at a dose of ≥3 g/day for over 4 weeks or documented intolerance to mesalazine (a documented intolerance required previous doctors' letters or medical notes that stated that an adverse event possibly related to mesalazine led to a discontinuation of its therapy); active disease with blood in stool for at least 6 weeks; SCCAI ≥5 and SCCAI subscore for “blood in stool” ≥2 at baseline visit (V2); comedication was allowed if on a stable dose for 4 weeks (e.g., 5-ASA, systemic acting steroids (if taken for ≥8 weeks before the start of the study), azathioprine (2–2.5 mg/kg), 6-mercaptopurine (1–1.5 mg/kg), both if taken for ≥3 months); and a negative pregnancy test at V1 and V2 plus the use of adequate contraception, if applicable. Exclusion criteria were as follows: toxic megacolon or fulminant courses; therapy with cyclosporine, tacrolimus, methotrexate, or TNF-α-antagonists within 3 months before study entry; current treatment with opiates or loperamide; current antibiotic treatment; rectal applications of aminosalicylates, steroids, or budesonide; oral application of topically acting steroids; ulcerative proctitis with a disease extent &lt;10 cm; inflammatory or bleeding disorders of the gastrointestinal tract other than UC, or diseases that may cause diarrhea or gastrointestinal bleeding; condition after surgery of the colon; any other uncontrolled systemic diseases (e.g., cardiac, renal, pulmonary, hepatic) or severe chronic diseases (e.g., malignancies, HIV infection); and pregnant or nursing women. 5-ASA, 5-aminosalicylic acid; AE, adverse event; Discont. Intervent., discontinued intervention; INR, international normalized ratio; SCCAI, Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α UC, ulcerative colitis. 
We calculated 160 patients with mesalazine-refractory UC for the screening phase in order to randomize 144 patients. A planned interim analysis included the possibility of increasing the sample size if necessary. The main inclusion criteria were as follows: an active disease with the Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index (SCCAI) of ≥5 and a subscore for “blood in stool” of ≥2 at baseline; a history of bloody diarrhea for at least 6 weeks before inclusion despite mesalazine treatment at a dose of ≥3 g/day; or a documented intolerance to mesalazine (for details of criteria, see legend of Figure 1). Patients were required to maintain a stable comedication throughout the study; steroid tapering was not allowed. UC was defined in accordance with the European consensus conference (21). Recruitment took place in 24 referral centers in Germany, Lithuania, and Romania. The Contract Research Organization (CRO) produced computer-generated randomization lists for every study center with the allocation of 1:1:1:1 in blocks of 4. The study interventions consisting of three different doses of LT-02 (0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g) were tested against placebo and were provided in sequentially numbered containers. Doses were selected based on the results of the previous studies (18,19,20). The study medication was provided in sachets with pellets taken orally four times daily. The study medication was produced, packed, and labeled according to Good Manufacturing Practice and stored at 2–8 °C.
      Patients were interviewed, examined, and screened for eligibility at the screening visit (V1, for inclusion and exclusion criteria see legend of Figure 1). Patients to be included received detailed study information, gave written informed consent, and were instructed in completing the study diary (comprising SCCAI and other interview parameters). Stool samples were taken to exclude for infectious enterocolitis (including Clostridium difficile and Escherichia coli 0157:H7). If the patient was still eligible after 1 week of screening (V2=baseline), a safety lab was taken and a sigmoidoscopy/colonoscopy was performed. At the interim visits 2 and 6 weeks after baseline (V3 and V4), possible disease exacerbation and changes in medication or adverse events (AEs) were assessed. The treatment period ended 12 weeks after baseline at V5 and involved an interview, a physical examination, a sigmoidoscopy, a safety lab, and the SCCAI assessment. The maximal duration of the study was 21 weeks per patient: a 1-week screening period plus 12 weeks of treatment period; patients reaching partial or complete remission (SCCAI &lt;5 at end of treatment) underwent an additional 8-week follow-up without study medication (see Appendix Figure A1).
      Patients could discontinue the study at any time without reason. The investigator could withdraw a patient in case of AEs or disease exacerbation or if therapeutic intervention was required. Discontinuation criteria were the development of complications such as pseudomembranous colitis, an SCCAI increase of ≥7 over baseline, or fever &gt;39 °C. Discontinuation because of disease exacerbation was defined as an AE. Patients who discontinued the study early qualified as “premature discontinuation” which resulted in a final study visit. Dropouts were not replaced.
      Patients' compliance was monitored by returned sachets, diary entries, and interviews. The central ethics committees approved the study protocol in all participating countries. No changes to the study methods were made after study initiation.
      
        Precautions against bias
        To avoid selection bias, all patients who fulfilled all criteria were included into the study in the predefined, randomized order. Pellets, sachets, and containers were completely indistinguishable between treatment arms. Both patients and study personnel remained blinded and unaware of the allocation method throughout the study until database closure. It was not possible for patients or investigators to guess the next allocated medication in order to avoid selection or allocation biases. To avoid attrition bias, we handled incomplete data in a conservative manner: all patients with premature treatment termination were included in all final analyses with their last available data (last observation carried forward (LOCF)), so that a possible LT-02 treatment effect was rather reduced than increased. More placebo patients may have stopped treatment owing to a lack of efficacy or for other reasons; it is unlikely that the results would have improved if treatment had been continued, and carrying forward the last value appeared to be conservative. All dropouts and losses to follow-up are described in Figure 1. Individuals with possible conflict of interest were neither allowed to recruit patients nor were they involved in the conduct or analyses of the study. There were no changes in the study methods or outcome parameters after study initiation. All authors had access to the study data and have reviewed and approved this manuscript.
      
      
        Outcomes
        The disease activity was assessed using the SCCAI (22) that is validated and has been proven to correlate well with other indices comprising invasive methods (23,24,25,26). The primary end point was changes in SCCAI from baseline (V2) to V5. The SCCAI assesses stool frequency during the day and at night, defecation urgency, blood in stool, general well-being, abdominal pain, and extraintestinal manifestations. The score ranges from 0 to 19 points—the lower the score, the lower the disease activity.
        We assessed the following secondary and a priori defined end points in an exploratory sense: complete remission (&lt;3 mean SCCAI (26) and “blood in stool” subscore of 0 (see European Crohn's and Colitis Organization (ECCO) definition of remission (21), LOCF); partial remission (SCCAI &lt;5, LOCF); clinical response (SCCAI decrease ≥2 (26); mucosal healing (endoscopic Mayo Score (EMS) ≤1); achievement of mucosal healing (EMS ≤1 at V5 and improvement of EMS ≥1 from V2 to V5); patients with complete remission; and a “bowel frequency” subscore of 0. All SCCAI-based end points refer to the patient's mean values of 1 week rounded to integer numbers. Time to symptom resolution was defined as the first 3 days with ≤3 stools per day without visible blood (21).
        The EMS is categorized as follows: 0, inactive; 1, mild disease (erythema, decreased vascular pattern, minimal granularity); 2, moderate disease (marked erythema, friability, granularity, absent vascular pattern, bleeding on minimal trauma, no ulcerations); and 3, severe disease (ulceration, spontaneous bleeding). The histologic index (by Riley) ranges from 1 representing remission to 4 representing severe colitis; a central pathologist, who was blinded to the groups, assessed the score.
      
      
        Statistics
        Data from a dose-finding study (19) showed that a relative effect size for the SCCAI of ∼0.8 could be expected from the 3.2 g dose group compared with placebo. Under the parametric assumptions of the t-test, 30 patients per group were needed to detect a difference of a relative effect size of 0.8 between placebo and an active group with a power of 85% (α=0.025, one sided). The sample size was increased from 30 to 36 patients per group to accommodate for nonresponse, loss to follow-up, and other deviations from planned study conditions. We also included dose groups of 0.8 and 1.6 g LT-02 to allow for dose-finding and dose-response analyses, as the drug LT-02 was new and had not been tested in studies.
        Primary analysis was based on the full analysis set (intention to treat) that included all randomized patients. If a patient had a missing value at the final visit (V5), the latest available value was carried forward. Analysis of covariance was used to model the primary end point, including the following baseline covariates: (i) mean SCCAI in the past 7 days of the screening period; and (ii) disease extent. The model including these two covariates and the treatment group effect was considered to be the core model. It was used to compare the effects of placebo and the individual dose groups in fixed sequence, starting with the highest dose group of 3.2 g LT-02 daily, followed by the lower dose groups in descending order. The confirmatory testing procedure stopped at the first nonsignificant result; superiority was given if the one-sided P value was &lt;0.025, equivalent to a two-sided α level of 0.05.
        Survival methods were used to analyze time-to-event variables; the log-rank test compared time with event curves between treatment groups. likelihood ratio χ2 tests based on nominal logistic regression were planned to compare the results of qualitative variables between treatment groups. The analysis plan did not specify how the groups should be compared: in order to increase the statistical power, we focused on the comparisons between placebo and the three active groups pooled.
        The statistical power to detect treatment effects in categorical parameters in this small sample size is far below the usual 80–90%. This is why we defined categorical variables such as rate of remission or mucosal healing a priori as secondary and exploratory, in order to discover trends in treatment effects to gather information for the sample-size calculation for future phase III studies.
        Linearity was checked for important continuous variables compared with log transformation. Normality for continuous parameters was assumed if the absolute value of skewness was&lt;1. In addition, the Shapiro–Wilk goodness-of-fit tests were applied.
        A planned interim analysis was conducted by an independent data monitoring committee after half of the patients had terminated the treatment period to adjust the sample size or to stop the trial for futility, if indicated.
        Software for sample-size estimation included nQuery Advisor V5.0 (Statistical Solutions Ltd, Cork, Ireland) and StudySize V2.0 (CREOSTAT HB, V.Frolunda, Sweden). Statistical analyses were performed using SAS JMP V9 and SAS JMP V8 and higher (JMP, SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC).
      
    
    
      RESULTS
      The study was conducted between November 2009 and December 2010. A total of 175 patients were screened, of which 156 UC patients (119 in Germany, 22 in Lithuania, and 15 in Romania) were randomized and treated (see Figure 1). When we received the recommendation of the independent data monitoring committee to continue the study as planned, we had already randomized 12 patients more than the planned 144 patients; the independent data monitoring committee then recommended including these additional patients in the analyses.
      In total, 14, 12, 6, and 7 patients of the placebo, 0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g LT-02 groups, respectively, terminated the study prematurely after randomization, most frequently at their own request owing to the lack of efficacy or AEs. In addition, 18 patients did not return all empty sachets of study medication and were therefore classified as noncompliant (7 placebo, 6 0.8 g LT-02, 2 1.6 g LT-02, and 3 3.2 g LT-02 patients). One placebo patient suffered a serious adverse event (SAE; atrial fibrillation) and was unblinded prematurely; one patient in the 3.2 g LT-02 group was accidentally unblinded by a peripheral study nurse, but remained single-blinded.
       Table 1 Key demographic and baseline characteristics 
Overall, disease-specific baseline characteristics indicated no major differences across the four patient groups (Table 1). There were no relevant country effects in the interaction analyses. Concomitant medication was comparable across all study groups, but azathioprine intake was higher in the 0.8 g LT-02 group. The mean SCCAI varied from 8.5 to 9.0, which represents a moderately active UC population. There were no colectomies reported during the study or during follow-up.
      
        Efficacy results
         Figure 2 Primary end-point analysis.The comparison between placebo and the highest dose group revealed an estimate of −1.56 and a two-sided P value of 0.03 with a 95% confidence interval of −2.96 to −0.16. SCCAI, Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index. 
We found a higher absolute SCCAI reduction in all LT-02 groups compared with placebo. In the primary analysis, the disease activity score (SCCAI) in the highest dose group (3.2 g LT-02) dropped from 8.5 to 4.1 (51.7%) compared with 9.0 to 6.0 (33.3%) in the placebo group (two-sided P value=0.030, see Figure 2; the corresponding one-sided P value is P=0.015 which met the goal of the study.)
         Figure 3 Time to first symptom resolution: all active LT-02 groups pooled vs. placebo. LT-02 patients reached the end point of first symptom resolution more than 2 weeks earlier than placebo (P=0.02, preplanned, two-sided log-rank test). In total, almost twice as many LT-02 patients reached complete symptom resolution compared with placebo. 
 Table 2 Further secondary end-point analyses 
The secondary analyses found a remission rate of 31.4% (11/35) in the highest LT-02 dose group compared with 15% (6/40) under placebo (P=0.09; two-sided likelihood ratio χ2 test; Appendix Figure A2). The response rates increased from 24/40 (60%) under placebo to 29/35 (83%) in the highest LT-02 dose group (P=0.030; two-sided likelihood ratio χ2 test; Table 2). The number needed to treat for LT-02 in mesalazine-refractory UC was 6.1 to reach complete remission and 4.3 to reach clinical response. The rate for achievement of mucosal healing was 32.5% in the placebo group compared with 47.4% in the pooled LT-02 groups (P=0.098, Table 2); the rate for histologic healing (histologic index=1) was 20.0% in the placebo compared with 35.3% in the LT-02 groups (P=0.016). The time to first symptom resolution was 33 days in the median among LT-02 responders. Symptom resolution occurred ∼2 weeks earlier and was almost twice as often under LT-02 treatment than under placebo treatment (P=0.02; Figure 3).
      
      
        Safety results
         Table 3 Drug-related adverse events as defined by the site investigator, n (%) 
Safety evaluations of lab results, vital signs, and physical examinations did not show any treatment-related changes between the study groups. The frequency of possibly drug-related AEs was low in all four study arms. Mainly mild or moderate treatment-related AEs occurred. There were 17 treatment-emergent AEs (48.6%) in the highest dose group (0 SAEs) compared with 22 (55%) in the placebo group (4 SAEs). There were no relevant or significant differences of adverse drug reactions between the treatment groups (see Table 3; Appendix Table A2). In all, 12 patients experienced 17 SAEs; these consisted of 5, 2, and 1 patient in the 0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g LT-02 treatment groups, respectively, and 4 patients in the placebo group. Only one SAE, atrial fibrillation, was assessed as being possibly related to study treatment; it occurred in the placebo group.
      
      
        Follow-up
        Responders of all study arms entered an 8-week follow-up period without study medication. Patients in the LT-02 group were able to avoid relapses over a longer period and in a higher percentage of patients (P=0.02, log-rank test; Appendix Figure A3).
      
    
    
      DISCUSSION
      The aim of the current trial was to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and optimal dose of a newly designed, modified release formulation of highly purified PC (LT-02). This drug is a first-in-class therapy for UC and the first treatment with a mucoprotective substance to reach study phase II or phase III.
      The primary analysis revealed a statistically significant treatment effect for LT-02 in mesalazine-refractory UC: whereas the two lower doses of LT-02 showed improvement that was statistically not significant, the highest LT-02 dose group (3.2 g) showed a significantly higher drop of the index compared with placebo (P=0.030, two sided). Mixed modeling was performed as sensitivity analyses for the SCCAI primary model to confirm the primary analysis: all data of visits under treatment were used as the dependent variable (without applying LOCF), with repeated measures on the same patient taken into account with three different versions of simple covariance structures of residuals. Fixed effects included into the mixed model were the same as in the primary model, namely dose group, SCCAI at baseline, and extent of disease. The resulting two-sided P values for the primary comparison of 3.2 g LT-02 vs. placebo were between 0.008 and 0.036 depending on the type of the covariance structure used. These analyses confirmed the statistical significance of the originally planned primary analysis.
      SCCAI subcategory analyses revealed that “Extraintestinal Manifestations” showed no significant differences between LT-02 and placebo, and this is not surprising for a topical and not systemic agent. “Bowel Movements at Night” indicated a statistical trend with a two-sided P value of 0.127, whereas “Stool Urgency” resulted in a P value of 0.006. (Both categories represent major patient complaints: nightly defecation is highly disruptive and affects patients' recreation; stool urgency requires immediate access to bathrooms, which may result in pain and humiliating stool incontinence.) “Bowel Frequency,” “General Wellbeing,” and “Blood In Stool” show borderline significant P values that are not much higher compared with those of the total SCCAI.
      In the main secondary outcome analyses, we found that the clinical and histologic remission rates doubled between placebo and the highest LT-02 dose groups. Approximately 50% more LT-02 than placebo patients achieved mucosal healing (P&lt;0.1, Table 2). As the applied LOCF analyses bear the risk of underestimating treatment effects (27), we conducted a sensitivity analysis upon request of reviewers with dropouts treated as failures: the effects that we observed magnified and indicated statistical significance (Table 2). The preplanned analyses of clinical response and time to first symptom resolution also revealed statistically significant results (Figure 3). Follow-up analyses revealed that placebo patients relapsed earlier and more frequently than LT-02 patients (P=0.02; Appendix Figure A3). This underlines the LT-02 efficacy as the placebo effect in the placebo group became more apparent. The treatment effect of LT-02 seems to last longer than the period of actual drug intake. We believe that an interruption of the vicious cycle of barrier defect and mucosal damage might be responsible for this effect.
      The treatment effects in mesalazine-refractory UC were good (number needed to treat was 6.1 for complete remission and 4.3 for clinical response), and the safety profile was excellent: AEs occurred equally among placebo and LT-02 groups and no LT-02-related SAE occurred.
      
        Limitations
        The primary end point “changes of disease activity index” instead of remission rates is unusual for a larger study. The clinical effect and the practical impact of treatment may be overestimated with the use of numerical changes, but they detect clinical effects in smaller study populations. Information is lost by qualitative variables such as remission rates. This is why quantitative target variables are important in dose-finding studies, as they have a higher sensitivity concerning dose-response effects of a new drug such as LT-02.
        On the basis of this primary, quantitative end point, we had planned to include 36 evaluable patients per group. Remission end points require much higher sample sizes of ∼200 patients per group (equals N=800 for this study), and these are targeted for pivotal studies. The small sample size of the current trial resulted in a reduced statistical power for secondary end points, making statistical significance unlikely. With our small sample size, success rate estimates of qualitative variables have a high variability; statistically significant results or strict dose-response patterns cannot be expected for qualitative parameters such as remission or mucosal healing.
        Most pivotal studies in UC use the Mayo score instead of the SCCAI. The European Medicines Agency, EMA, however, states that it does not favor any score, but recommends the use of indices using signs and symptoms rather than endoscopy, as this correlates well with the former but varies strongly between observers (www.tga.gov.au/pdf/euguide/ewp1846306en.pdf). The SCCAI is the most comprehensive clinical score; it requires no diagnostic interventions and allows for continuous evaluation throughout the study. Unlike the Mayo or CAI scores, it allows for time-to-event (remission/response) analyses (see Figure 3, Appendix Table A1 and Appendix Figure A3) that are essential for a new drug with an unknown time to treatment response. The SCCAI is a relatively new, but well-established, score that has been used frequently in clinical studies recently. Cutoff points for remission (&lt;2.5), relapse (&gt;4.5), and response (index drop &gt;1.5) have been validated (24,25,26). As the SCCAI only allows for natural numbers, our end points of remission &lt;3, partial remission ≤5, and response (SCCAI drop ≥2) are equivalent to these cutoffs.
        Of the 24 study centers, 9 had &lt;4 patients and an additional 7 centers had &lt;8 patients, and this explains a certain deviation from a better balance between study arms (N varies between 35 and 41). This, however, is not an issue because statistical tests are fitted more to simple randomization than to restricted randomization.
        The randomization ratio was 1:1:1:1 with blocks of four per center. This could mean a potential limited bias in case of the premature unblinding of a patient, as the investigators might draw conclusions concerning the treatment of the remaining patients at their centers. In an isolated occurrence, a patient was accidentally unblinded by a study nurse. As the investigators were completely uninformed regarding the above-described packaging strategy, it is highly unlikely that this could influence the study outcome. A randomization ratio with blocks of eight would have been preferable, but it was financially not feasible.
        Some authors expect a two-sided P value for the primary analysis. A one-sided P value, however, is often used in regulatory superiority studies with a stricter significance level of P=0.025 that equals a two-sided P value of 0.05. Inferiority to placebo was not assumed, as previous studies had shown superiority. All presented P values are two sided; only the P value for the primary analysis is presented as both one and two sided to facilitate the comparison with the stricter limit of 0.025.
        Fecal calprotectin is an essential marker in UC at present. During the planning phase of the study, however, it was not established and was included into the running study. As the study progressed so fast, the resulting data are too little to be analyzed.
      
      
        Conclusion
        There is a pressing need for treatment alternatives in refractory UC. The goal of the study with the a priori defined primary end point of changes in disease activity was reached: the disease activity score dropped significantly under 3.2 g LT-02 compared with placebo. Moreover, the drug was found to be very safe. Although the improvement of the disease activity in the lower doses (0.8 and 1.6 g LT-02) was not statistically significant compared with placebo, the highest dose was effective and is intended for the planned pivotal studies.
        The treatment effects of modified release PC appear to correlate with the shift of paradigm from immunological disorder to mucosal barrier dysfunction that has taken place in our understanding of inflammatory bowel disease in recent years. Our findings could possibly further the treatment and understanding of ulcerative colitis.
      
    
    
      Study Highlights
              
    
  

Back matter

      We thank the following people for their help in recruiting and managing study patients in Germany: Sabine Stoffels, Annika Braun, and Robert Ehehalt (Heidelberg); Susanna Nikolaus, Tanja Kühbacher, Dörthe Schuldt, and Johannes Bethge (Kiel); Jana Berthold (Ulm); Bernd Bokemeyer (Minden); Sven and Sigrid Gehrke (Baden Baden); Babett Holler and Niels Teich (Leipzig); Stefanie Howaldt (Hamburg); Frank Lammert and Marc Dauer (Homburg); Christian Maaser (Lüneburg); Max Reinshagen (Braunschweig); Andreas Stallmach (Jena). We also thank Remigijus Garalevicius, Gediminas Kiudelis, Gintautas Radziunas, Romualdas Jurgutis, Laimas Jonaitis, and Gediminas Kiudelis (Lithuania); Adrian Goldis, Amelita Tirnaveanu, Christian Banciu, and Claudia Iacobescu (Romania). We thank Heather Karner and Janet Collins for proofreading the manuscript. We also thank Dr Michael Vieth from Bayreuth Hospital for providing the histological evaluation. Pierrel Research (CRO) was responsible for the planning, organization, and statistical analyses of the study. After unblinding the study, Winfried Koch verified the primary and secondary analyses and provided additional statistical support for the publication; he contributed to the statistics section.
    

      
        Appendix
           
      
    

      Guarantor of the article: Max Karner, MD.
      Specific author contributions: M.K. was the principal investigator of the study; he helped in the planning and conduct of the trial and prepared the manuscript; he had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. A.K., J.S., S.S., G.v.B., P.U., C.S., L.K., and I.D. were the site investigators of the most active study centers. F.Z. and G.K. are representatives of Lipid Therapeutics (sponsor), Heidelberg, Germany, and helped in the planning and organization of the study. W.S. is the inventor of mrPC; he helped in the study design and prepared the manuscript together with M.K.
      Financial support: Lipid Therapeutics (Heidelberg, Germany) is the sponsor of the study and financed the conduct of the study, the CRO, the second statistician, as well as the Data Monitoring Committee. The investigators themselves did not receive money from the sponsor, but the study centers were reimbursed for their work with patients. The study sponsor helped plan the study design and financed the CRO. The CRO, but not the sponsor, managed the conduct of the study, performed the study analyses, and interpreted the data. The sponsor was neither involved in the data collection nor in the preparation of the manuscript.
      Potential competing interests: M.K. was reimbursed for his costs to present the study data at a national and an international congress. A.K., J.S., S.S., G.B., P.U., C.S., L.K., and I.D. had no potential conflict of interest. F.Z. and G.K. are representatives of the sponsor. The adult and independent children of W.S. hold the patent for modified release phosphatidylcholine. W.S., F.Z., and G.K. were not involved in patient recruitment, conduct, or analyses of the study. Moreover, F.Z. and G.K., as representatives of the sponsor, were not involved in the preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript, nor in the decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</text>
    <sentence charOffset="0-5" id="S1">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Title</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6-172" id="S2" selection="1a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">First Multicenter Study of Modified Release Phosphatidylcholine “LT-02” in Ulcerative Colitis: A Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial in Mesalazine-Refractory Courses</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="173-181" id="S3">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Abstract</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="202-213" id="S4" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">OBJECTIVES:</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="224-286" id="S5" selection="1b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Phosphatidylcholine is a key component of the mucosal barrier.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="287-385" id="S6" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Treatment with modified release phosphatidylcholine aims to improve the impaired barrier function.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="386-534" id="S7" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary objective is to evaluate the efficacy of LT-02, a newly designed modified release phosphatidylcholine formula, in a multicenter setting.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="563-571" id="S8" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">METHODS:</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="582-737" id="S9" selection="3a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This is a double-blinded, randomized, placebo-controlled, superiority study conducted in 24 ambulatory referral centers in Germany, Lithuania, and Romania.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="738-959" id="S10" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A total of 156 patients with an inadequate response to mesalazine, a disease activity score (Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index (SCCAI)) of ≥5, and bloody diarrhea underwent treatment with 0, 0.8, 1.6, or 3.2 g LT-02.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="960-1061" id="S11" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary end point was defined a priori as changes in SCCAI from baseline to the end of treatment.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1062-1133" id="S12" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary statistical model was a general linear least-squares model.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1134-1272" id="S13" selection="23,25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study was funded by the sponsor Lipid Therapeutics, Heidelberg, Germany, and registered at http://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01011322.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1301-1309" id="S14" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">RESULTS:</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1320-1396" id="S15" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Baseline characteristics and dropouts were well balanced between all groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1397-1617" id="S16" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary analyses revealed an SCCAI drop of 33.3% in the placebo group (from 9.0 to 6.0 points) compared with 44.3% in the 0.8 g LT-02 (from 8.8 to 4.9, P&gt;0.05) and 40.7% in the 1.6 g groups (from 8.6 to 5.1, P&gt;0.05).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1618-1702" id="S17" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The 3.2 g group improved 51.7% from 8.5 to 4.1 (P=0.030 in comparison with placebo).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1703-1828" id="S18" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The remission rate was 15% (6/40) in the placebo group compared with 31.4% (11/35) in the highest LT-02 dose group (P=0.089).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1829-2024" id="S19" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Mucosal healing was achieved in 32.5% of placebo patients compared with 47.4% of LT-02 patients (P=0.098); the rates for histologic remission were 20% compared with 40.5%, respectively (P=0.016).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2025-2198" id="S20" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were 17 (48.6%) treatment-emergent adverse events in the highest dose group (and 0 serious adverse events (SAEs)) compared with 22 (55%) in the placebo group (4 SAEs).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2227-2239" id="S21" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">CONCLUSIONS:</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2250-2398" id="S22" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary end point analysis showed a statistically significant improvement in disease activity during LT-02 treatment in comparison with placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2399-2434" id="S23" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The drug was found to be very safe.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2451-2618" id="S24" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table A2b Detailed listing of adverse events  Table A2a Categories of adverse events (AEs)  Table A2c Serious adverse events (SAEs)  Table A1 Remission rates over time</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2637-2649" id="S25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">INTRODUCTION</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2656-2788" id="S26" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Ulcerative colitis (UC) is an inflammatory bowel disease that affects the distal colon, potentially spreading over the entire colon.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2789-2877" id="S27" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The incidence is 5—20/100,000 in western countries, with a prevalence of 0.02—0.23% (1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2878-2975" id="S28" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">First-line pharmacotherapy consists of 5-aminosalicylic acids and/or steroids for acute episodes.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2976-3067" id="S29" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Aminosalicylates and thiopurines, but not steroids, should be used for maintenance therapy.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3068-3293" id="S30" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Calcineurin and tumor necrosis factor-α antagonists may work in refractory cases, but the effects wear off over time and adverse events can be limiting (2,3,4,5); see also FDA block warning on tumor necrosis factor blockers).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3294-3363" id="S31" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Moreover, tumor necrosis factor antibodies are highly cost intensive.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3364-3429" id="S32" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Current therapeutic regimens therefore are not always successful.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3430-3482" id="S33" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The 10-year cumulative risk of colectomy is ∼9% (6).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3483-3546" id="S34" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">An unmet medical need for a safe and effective therapy remains.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3553-3653" id="S35" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Phosphatidylcholine (PC) was found to be an essential protective component of colonic mucus (7,8,9).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3654-3876" id="S36" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The novel treatment of modified release PC was based on the observation that specifically patients with UC had a low intrinsic mucus PC content that reduces the hydrophobic barrier function of the intestinal mucus (10,11).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3877-4046" id="S37" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Colonic bacteria may then permeate the intestinal mucus barrier, and the consecutive unspecific but aggressive immune responses lead to inflammation and ulceration (12).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4047-4170" id="S38" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Moreover, the intrinsic anti-inflammatory property of PC is lacking which, in turn, perpetuates the mucosal damage (13,14).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4171-4305" id="S39" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The purpose of modified release PC is to reconstitute the low mucus PC reservoir and to re-establish the mucosal barrier (9,15,16,17).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4306-4431" id="S40" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Three previous studies have shown efficacy using a modified release preparation of soy lecithin containing 30% PC (18,19,20).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4432-4568" id="S41" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The altered bioavailability of modified release PC aims to release PC in the distal ileum, thereby avoiding early intestinal absorption.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4569-4688" id="S42" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The formula was optimized to LT-02, which contains &gt;94% PC concentrated soy lecithin, to allow for regulatory approval.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4695-4798" id="S43" selection="2b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The goal of the present trial was to evaluate the clinical efficacy, optimal dose, and safety of LT-02.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4815-4822" id="S44">
        <text xml:space="preserve">METHODS</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4830-4855" id="S45" selection="13a,13b,16">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 1 Study flowchart.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4856-5765" id="S46" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Inclusion criteria were as follows: proven mesalazine-refractory ulcerative colitis (European consensus definition (16) with an inadequate response to mesalazine for 6 weeks at a dose of ≥3 g/day for over 4 weeks or documented intolerance to mesalazine (a documented intolerance required previous doctors' letters or medical notes that stated that an adverse event possibly related to mesalazine led to a discontinuation of its therapy); active disease with blood in stool for at least 6 weeks; SCCAI ≥5 and SCCAI subscore for “blood in stool” ≥2 at baseline visit (V2); comedication was allowed if on a stable dose for 4 weeks (e.g., 5-ASA, systemic acting steroids (if taken for ≥8 weeks before the start of the study), azathioprine (2–2.5 mg/kg), 6-mercaptopurine (1–1.5 mg/kg), both if taken for ≥3 months); and a negative pregnancy test at V1 and V2 plus the use of adequate contraception, if applicable.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5766-6552" id="S47" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Exclusion criteria were as follows: toxic megacolon or fulminant courses; therapy with cyclosporine, tacrolimus, methotrexate, or TNF-α-antagonists within 3 months before study entry; current treatment with opiates or loperamide; current antibiotic treatment; rectal applications of aminosalicylates, steroids, or budesonide; oral application of topically acting steroids; ulcerative proctitis with a disease extent &lt;10 cm; inflammatory or bleeding disorders of the gastrointestinal tract other than UC, or diseases that may cause diarrhea or gastrointestinal bleeding; condition after surgery of the colon; any other uncontrolled systemic diseases (e.g., cardiac, renal, pulmonary, hepatic) or severe chronic diseases (e.g., malignancies, HIV infection); and pregnant or nursing women.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6553-6610" id="S48" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">5-ASA, 5-aminosalicylic acid; AE, adverse event; Discont.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6611-6788" id="S49" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Intervent., discontinued intervention; INR, international normalized ratio; SCCAI, Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index; TNF-α, tumor necrosis factor-α UC, ulcerative colitis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6790-6906" id="S50" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We calculated 160 patients with mesalazine-refractory UC for the screening phase in order to randomize 144 patients.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6907-7002" id="S51" selection="7b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A planned interim analysis included the possibility of increasing the sample size if necessary.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7003-7394" id="S52" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The main inclusion criteria were as follows: an active disease with the Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index (SCCAI) of ≥5 and a subscore for “blood in stool” of ≥2 at baseline; a history of bloody diarrhea for at least 6 weeks before inclusion despite mesalazine treatment at a dose of ≥3 g/day; or a documented intolerance to mesalazine (for details of criteria, see legend of Figure 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7395-7507" id="S53" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients were required to maintain a stable comedication throughout the study; steroid tapering was not allowed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7508-7581" id="S54" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">UC was defined in accordance with the European consensus conference (21).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7582-7663" id="S55" selection="4b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Recruitment took place in 24 referral centers in Germany, Lithuania, and Romania.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7664-7822" id="S56" selection="8a,8b,10">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The Contract Research Organization (CRO) produced computer-generated randomization lists for every study center with the allocation of 1:1:1:1 in blocks of 4.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7823-7996" id="S57" selection="9,5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study interventions consisting of three different doses of LT-02 (0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g) were tested against placebo and were provided in sequentially numbered containers.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7997-8073" id="S58" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Doses were selected based on the results of the previous studies (18,19,20).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8074-8162" id="S59" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study medication was provided in sachets with pellets taken orally four times daily.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8163-8280" id="S60" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study medication was produced, packed, and labeled according to Good Manufacturing Practice and stored at 2–8 °C.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8287-8442" id="S61" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients were interviewed, examined, and screened for eligibility at the screening visit (V1, for inclusion and exclusion criteria see legend of Figure 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8443-8635" id="S62" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients to be included received detailed study information, gave written informed consent, and were instructed in completing the study diary (comprising SCCAI and other interview parameters).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8636-8764" id="S63" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Stool samples were taken to exclude for infectious enterocolitis (including Clostridium difficile and Escherichia coli 0157:H7).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8765-8909" id="S64" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">If the patient was still eligible after 1 week of screening (V2=baseline), a safety lab was taken and a sigmoidoscopy/colonoscopy was performed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8910-9068" id="S65" selection="7b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the interim visits 2 and 6 weeks after baseline (V3 and V4), possible disease exacerbation and changes in medication or adverse events (AEs) were assessed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9069-9233" id="S66" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The treatment period ended 12 weeks after baseline at V5 and involved an interview, a physical examination, a sigmoidoscopy, a safety lab, and the SCCAI assessment.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9234-9525" id="S67" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The maximal duration of the study was 21 weeks per patient: a 1-week screening period plus 12 weeks of treatment period; patients reaching partial or complete remission (SCCAI &lt;5 at end of treatment) underwent an additional 8-week follow-up without study medication (see Appendix Figure A1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9532-9596" id="S68" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients could discontinue the study at any time without reason.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9597-9722" id="S69" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The investigator could withdraw a patient in case of AEs or disease exacerbation or if therapeutic intervention was required.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9723-9945" id="S70" selection="7b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Discontinuation criteria were the development of complications such as pseudomembranous colitis, an SCCAI increase of ≥7 over baseline, or fever &gt;39 °C. Discontinuation because of disease exacerbation was defined as an AE.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9946-10067" id="S71" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients who discontinued the study early qualified as “premature discontinuation” which resulted in a final study visit.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10068-10095" id="S72" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Dropouts were not replaced.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10102-10188" id="S73" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients' compliance was monitored by returned sachets, diary entries, and interviews.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10189-10278" id="S74" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The central ethics committees approved the study protocol in all participating countries.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10279-10344" id="S75" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">No changes to the study methods were made after study initiation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10360-10384" id="S76" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Precautions against bias</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10393-10523" id="S77" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">To avoid selection bias, all patients who fulfilled all criteria were included into the study in the predefined, randomized order.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10524-10614" id="S78" selection="11b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Pellets, sachets, and containers were completely indistinguishable between treatment arms.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10615-10747" id="S79" selection="11a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Both patients and study personnel remained blinded and unaware of the allocation method throughout the study until database closure.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10748-10886" id="S80" selection="11a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">It was not possible for patients or investigators to guess the next allocated medication in order to avoid selection or allocation biases.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10887-11201" id="S81" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">To avoid attrition bias, we handled incomplete data in a conservative manner: all patients with premature treatment termination were included in all final analyses with their last available data (last observation carried forward (LOCF)), so that a possible LT-02 treatment effect was rather reduced than increased.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11202-11450" id="S82" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">More placebo patients may have stopped treatment owing to a lack of efficacy or for other reasons; it is unlikely that the results would have improved if treatment had been continued, and carrying forward the last value appeared to be conservative.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11451-11514" id="S83" selection="13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All dropouts and losses to follow-up are described in Figure 1.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11515-11666" id="S84" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Individuals with possible conflict of interest were neither allowed to recruit patients nor were they involved in the conduct or analyses of the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11667-11755" id="S85" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were no changes in the study methods or outcome parameters after study initiation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11756-11844" id="S86" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All authors had access to the study data and have reviewed and approved this manuscript.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11867-11875" id="S87" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Outcomes</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11884-12056" id="S88" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The disease activity was assessed using the SCCAI (22) that is validated and has been proven to correlate well with other indices comprising invasive methods (23,24,25,26).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12057-12125" id="S89" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary end point was changes in SCCAI from baseline (V2) to V5.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12126-12297" id="S90" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The SCCAI assesses stool frequency during the day and at night, defecation urgency, blood in stool, general well-being, abdominal pain, and extraintestinal manifestations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12298-12387" id="S91" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The score ranges from 0 to 19 points—the lower the score, the lower the disease activity.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12396-12942" id="S92" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We assessed the following secondary and a priori defined end points in an exploratory sense: complete remission (&lt;3 mean SCCAI (26) and “blood in stool” subscore of 0 (see European Crohn's and Colitis Organization (ECCO) definition of remission (21), LOCF); partial remission (SCCAI &lt;5, LOCF); clinical response (SCCAI decrease ≥2 (26); mucosal healing (endoscopic Mayo Score (EMS) ≤1); achievement of mucosal healing (EMS ≤1 at V5 and improvement of EMS ≥1 from V2 to V5); patients with complete remission; and a “bowel frequency” subscore of 0.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12943-13042" id="S93" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All SCCAI-based end points refer to the patient's mean values of 1 week rounded to integer numbers.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13043-13152" id="S94" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Time to symptom resolution was defined as the first 3 days with ≤3 stools per day without visible blood (21).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13161-13476" id="S95" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The EMS is categorized as follows: 0, inactive; 1, mild disease (erythema, decreased vascular pattern, minimal granularity); 2, moderate disease (marked erythema, friability, granularity, absent vascular pattern, bleeding on minimal trauma, no ulcerations); and 3, severe disease (ulceration, spontaneous bleeding).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13477-13653" id="S96" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The histologic index (by Riley) ranges from 1 representing remission to 4 representing severe colitis; a central pathologist, who was blinded to the groups, assessed the score.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13676-13686" id="S97" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Statistics</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13695-13854" id="S98" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data from a dose-finding study (19) showed that a relative effect size for the SCCAI of ∼0.8 could be expected from the 3.2 g dose group compared with placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13855-14070" id="S99" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Under the parametric assumptions of the t-test, 30 patients per group were needed to detect a difference of a relative effect size of 0.8 between placebo and an active group with a power of 85% (α=0.025, one sided).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14071-14236" id="S100" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The sample size was increased from 30 to 36 patients per group to accommodate for nonresponse, loss to follow-up, and other deviations from planned study conditions.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14237-14404" id="S101" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We also included dose groups of 0.8 and 1.6 g LT-02 to allow for dose-finding and dose-response analyses, as the drug LT-02 was new and had not been tested in studies.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14413-14524" id="S102" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Primary analysis was based on the full analysis set (intention to treat) that included all randomized patients.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14525-14630" id="S103" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">If a patient had a missing value at the final visit (V5), the latest available value was carried forward.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14631-14823" id="S104" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Analysis of covariance was used to model the primary end point, including the following baseline covariates: (i) mean SCCAI in the past 7 days of the screening period; and (ii) disease extent.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14824-14932" id="S105" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The model including these two covariates and the treatment group effect was considered to be the core model.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14933-15142" id="S106" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">It was used to compare the effects of placebo and the individual dose groups in fixed sequence, starting with the highest dose group of 3.2 g LT-02 daily, followed by the lower dose groups in descending order.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15143-15323" id="S107" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The confirmatory testing procedure stopped at the first nonsignificant result; superiority was given if the one-sided P value was &lt;0.025, equivalent to a two-sided α level of 0.05.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15332-15470" id="S108" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Survival methods were used to analyze time-to-event variables; the log-rank test compared time with event curves between treatment groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15471-15620" id="S109" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">likelihood ratio χ2 tests based on nominal logistic regression were planned to compare the results of qualitative variables between treatment groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15621-15815" id="S110" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The analysis plan did not specify how the groups should be compared: in order to increase the statistical power, we focused on the comparisons between placebo and the three active groups pooled.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15824-15956" id="S111" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The statistical power to detect treatment effects in categorical parameters in this small sample size is far below the usual 80–90%.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15957-16218" id="S112" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This is why we defined categorical variables such as rate of remission or mucosal healing a priori as secondary and exploratory, in order to discover trends in treatment effects to gather information for the sample-size calculation for future phase III studies.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16227-16317" id="S113" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Linearity was checked for important continuous variables compared with log transformation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16318-16406" id="S114" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Normality for continuous parameters was assumed if the absolute value of skewness was&lt;1.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16407-16472" id="S115" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In addition, the Shapiro–Wilk goodness-of-fit tests were applied.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16481-16703" id="S116" selection="7b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A planned interim analysis was conducted by an independent data monitoring committee after half of the patients had terminated the treatment period to adjust the sample size or to stop the trial for futility, if indicated.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16712-16873" id="S117" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Software for sample-size estimation included nQuery Advisor V5.0 (Statistical Solutions Ltd, Cork, Ireland) and StudySize V2.0 (CREOSTAT HB, V.Frolunda, Sweden).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16874-16989" id="S118" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Statistical analyses were performed using SAS JMP V9 and SAS JMP V8 and higher (JMP, SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17013-17020" id="S119">
        <text xml:space="preserve">RESULTS</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17027-17091" id="S120" selection="14a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study was conducted between November 2009 and December 2010.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17092-17252" id="S121" selection="4b,16">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A total of 175 patients were screened, of which 156 UC patients (119 in Germany, 22 in Lithuania, and 15 in Romania) were randomized and treated (see Figure 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17253-17553" id="S122" selection="13a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">When we received the recommendation of the independent data monitoring committee to continue the study as planned, we had already randomized 12 patients more than the planned 144 patients; the independent data monitoring committee then recommended including these additional patients in the analyses.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17560-17788" id="S123" selection="13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In total, 14, 12, 6, and 7 patients of the placebo, 0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g LT-02 groups, respectively, terminated the study prematurely after randomization, most frequently at their own request owing to the lack of efficacy or AEs.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17789-17983" id="S124" selection="13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In addition, 18 patients did not return all empty sachets of study medication and were therefore classified as noncompliant (7 placebo, 6 0.8 g LT-02, 2 1.6 g LT-02, and 3 3.2 g LT-02 patients).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17984-18216" id="S125" selection="13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">One placebo patient suffered a serious adverse event (SAE; atrial fibrillation) and was unblinded prematurely; one patient in the 3.2 g LT-02 group was accidentally unblinded by a peripheral study nurse, but remained single-blinded.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18224-18276" id="S126" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 1 Key demographic and baseline characteristics</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18278-18401" id="S127" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Overall, disease-specific baseline characteristics indicated no major differences across the four patient groups (Table 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18402-18469" id="S128" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were no relevant country effects in the interaction analyses.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18470-18593" id="S129" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Concomitant medication was comparable across all study groups, but azathioprine intake was higher in the 0.8 g LT-02 group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18594-18684" id="S130" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The mean SCCAI varied from 8.5 to 9.0, which represents a moderately active UC population.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18685-18757" id="S131" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were no colectomies reported during the study or during follow-up.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18773-18789" id="S132" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Efficacy results</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18799-19004" id="S133" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 2 Primary end-point analysis.The comparison between placebo and the highest dose group revealed an estimate of −1.56 and a two-sided P value of 0.03 with a 95% confidence interval of −2.96 to −0.16.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19005-19051" id="S134" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">SCCAI, Simple Clinical Colitis Activity Index.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19053-19138" id="S135" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We found a higher absolute SCCAI reduction in all LT-02 groups compared with placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19139-19445" id="S136" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the primary analysis, the disease activity score (SCCAI) in the highest dose group (3.2 g LT-02) dropped from 8.5 to 4.1 (51.7%) compared with 9.0 to 6.0 (33.3%) in the placebo group (two-sided P value=0.030, see Figure 2; the corresponding one-sided P value is P=0.015 which met the goal of the study.)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19455-19541" id="S137" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 3 Time to first symptom resolution: all active LT-02 groups pooled vs. placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19542-19692" id="S138" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">LT-02 patients reached the end point of first symptom resolution more than 2 weeks earlier than placebo (P=0.02, preplanned, two-sided log-rank test).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19693-19797" id="S139" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In total, almost twice as many LT-02 patients reached complete symptom resolution compared with placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19800-19844" id="S140" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 2 Further secondary end-point analyses</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19846-20045" id="S141" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The secondary analyses found a remission rate of 31.4% (11/35) in the highest LT-02 dose group compared with 15% (6/40) under placebo (P=0.09; two-sided likelihood ratio χ2 test; Appendix Figure A2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20046-20208" id="S142" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The response rates increased from 24/40 (60%) under placebo to 29/35 (83%) in the highest LT-02 dose group (P=0.030; two-sided likelihood ratio χ2 test; Table 2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20209-20345" id="S143" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The number needed to treat for LT-02 in mesalazine-refractory UC was 6.1 to reach complete remission and 4.3 to reach clinical response.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20346-20616" id="S144" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The rate for achievement of mucosal healing was 32.5% in the placebo group compared with 47.4% in the pooled LT-02 groups (P=0.098, Table 2); the rate for histologic healing (histologic index=1) was 20.0% in the placebo compared with 35.3% in the LT-02 groups (P=0.016).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20617-20703" id="S145" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The time to first symptom resolution was 33 days in the median among LT-02 responders.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20704-20849" id="S146" selection="17a,17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Symptom resolution occurred ∼2 weeks earlier and was almost twice as often under LT-02 treatment than under placebo treatment (P=0.02; Figure 3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20872-20886" id="S147" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Safety results</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20896-20974" id="S148" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 3 Drug-related adverse events as defined by the site investigator, n (%)</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20976-21118" id="S149" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Safety evaluations of lab results, vital signs, and physical examinations did not show any treatment-related changes between the study groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21119-21193" id="S150" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The frequency of possibly drug-related AEs was low in all four study arms.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21194-21249" id="S151" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Mainly mild or moderate treatment-related AEs occurred.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21250-21383" id="S152" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were 17 treatment-emergent AEs (48.6%) in the highest dose group (0 SAEs) compared with 22 (55%) in the placebo group (4 SAEs).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21384-21522" id="S153" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There were no relevant or significant differences of adverse drug reactions between the treatment groups (see Table 3; Appendix Table A2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21523-21704" id="S154" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In all, 12 patients experienced 17 SAEs; these consisted of 5, 2, and 1 patient in the 0.8, 1.6, and 3.2 g LT-02 treatment groups, respectively, and 4 patients in the placebo group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21705-21832" id="S155" selection="19">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Only one SAE, atrial fibrillation, was assessed as being possibly related to study treatment; it occurred in the placebo group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21855-21864" id="S156" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Follow-up</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21873-21962" id="S157" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Responders of all study arms entered an 8-week follow-up period without study medication.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21963-22123" id="S158" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Patients in the LT-02 group were able to avoid relapses over a longer period and in a higher percentage of patients (P=0.02, log-rank test; Appendix Figure A3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22147-22157" id="S159">
        <text xml:space="preserve">DISCUSSION</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22164-22328" id="S160" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The aim of the current trial was to evaluate the efficacy, safety, and optimal dose of a newly designed, modified release formulation of highly purified PC (LT-02).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22329-22467" id="S161" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This drug is a first-in-class therapy for UC and the first treatment with a mucoprotective substance to reach study phase II or phase III.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22474-22812" id="S162" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary analysis revealed a statistically significant treatment effect for LT-02 in mesalazine-refractory UC: whereas the two lower doses of LT-02 showed improvement that was statistically not significant, the highest LT-02 dose group (3.2 g) showed a significantly higher drop of the index compared with placebo (P=0.030, two sided).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22813-23160" id="S163" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Mixed modeling was performed as sensitivity analyses for the SCCAI primary model to confirm the primary analysis: all data of visits under treatment were used as the dependent variable (without applying LOCF), with repeated measures on the same patient taken into account with three different versions of simple covariance structures of residuals.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23161-23304" id="S164" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Fixed effects included into the mixed model were the same as in the primary model, namely dose group, SCCAI at baseline, and extent of disease.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23305-23476" id="S165" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The resulting two-sided P values for the primary comparison of 3.2 g LT-02 vs. placebo were between 0.008 and 0.036 depending on the type of the covariance structure used.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23477-23574" id="S166" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">These analyses confirmed the statistical significance of the originally planned primary analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23581-23780" id="S167" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">SCCAI subcategory analyses revealed that “Extraintestinal Manifestations” showed no significant differences between LT-02 and placebo, and this is not surprising for a topical and not systemic agent.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23781-23928" id="S168" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">“Bowel Movements at Night” indicated a statistical trend with a two-sided P value of 0.127, whereas “Stool Urgency” resulted in a P value of 0.006.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23929-24334" id="S169" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">(Both categories represent major patient complaints: nightly defecation is highly disruptive and affects patients' recreation; stool urgency requires immediate access to bathrooms, which may result in pain and humiliating stool incontinence.) “Bowel Frequency,” “General Wellbeing,” and “Blood In Stool” show borderline significant P values that are not much higher compared with those of the total SCCAI.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24341-24497" id="S170" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the main secondary outcome analyses, we found that the clinical and histologic remission rates doubled between placebo and the highest LT-02 dose groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24498-24591" id="S171" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Approximately 50% more LT-02 than placebo patients achieved mucosal healing (P&lt;0.1, Table 2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24592-24863" id="S172" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">As the applied LOCF analyses bear the risk of underestimating treatment effects (27), we conducted a sensitivity analysis upon request of reviewers with dropouts treated as failures: the effects that we observed magnified and indicated statistical significance (Table 2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="24864-25005" id="S173" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The preplanned analyses of clinical response and time to first symptom resolution also revealed statistically significant results (Figure 3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25006-25142" id="S174" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Follow-up analyses revealed that placebo patients relapsed earlier and more frequently than LT-02 patients (P=0.02; Appendix Figure A3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25143-25242" id="S175" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This underlines the LT-02 efficacy as the placebo effect in the placebo group became more apparent.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25243-25332" id="S176" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The treatment effect of LT-02 seems to last longer than the period of actual drug intake.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25333-25460" id="S177" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We believe that an interruption of the vicious cycle of barrier defect and mucosal damage might be responsible for this effect.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25467-25738" id="S178" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The treatment effects in mesalazine-refractory UC were good (number needed to treat was 6.1 for complete remission and 4.3 for clinical response), and the safety profile was excellent: AEs occurred equally among placebo and LT-02 groups and no LT-02-related SAE occurred.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25754-25765" id="S179" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Limitations</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25774-25889" id="S180" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary end point “changes of disease activity index” instead of remission rates is unusual for a larger study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="25890-26066" id="S181" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The clinical effect and the practical impact of treatment may be overestimated with the use of numerical changes, but they detect clinical effects in smaller study populations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26067-26136" id="S182" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Information is lost by qualitative variables such as remission rates.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26137-26313" id="S183" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This is why quantitative target variables are important in dose-finding studies, as they have a higher sensitivity concerning dose-response effects of a new drug such as LT-02.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26322-26434" id="S184" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">On the basis of this primary, quantitative end point, we had planned to include 36 evaluable patients per group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26435-26590" id="S185" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Remission end points require much higher sample sizes of ∼200 patients per group (equals N=800 for this study), and these are targeted for pivotal studies.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26591-26741" id="S186" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The small sample size of the current trial resulted in a reduced statistical power for secondary end points, making statistical significance unlikely.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="26742-26993" id="S187" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">With our small sample size, success rate estimates of qualitative variables have a high variability; statistically significant results or strict dose-response patterns cannot be expected for qualitative parameters such as remission or mucosal healing.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27002-27069" id="S188" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Most pivotal studies in UC use the Mayo score instead of the SCCAI.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27070-27362" id="S189" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The European Medicines Agency, EMA, however, states that it does not favor any score, but recommends the use of indices using signs and symptoms rather than endoscopy, as this correlates well with the former but varies strongly between observers (www.tga.gov.au/pdf/euguide/ewp1846306en.pdf).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27363-27513" id="S190" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The SCCAI is the most comprehensive clinical score; it requires no diagnostic interventions and allows for continuous evaluation throughout the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27514-27737" id="S191" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Unlike the Mayo or CAI scores, it allows for time-to-event (remission/response) analyses (see Figure 3, Appendix Table A1 and Appendix Figure A3) that are essential for a new drug with an unknown time to treatment response.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27738-27856" id="S192" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The SCCAI is a relatively new, but well-established, score that has been used frequently in clinical studies recently.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27857-27971" id="S193" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Cutoff points for remission (&lt;2.5), relapse (&gt;4.5), and response (index drop &gt;1.5) have been validated (24,25,26).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="27972-28133" id="S194" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">As the SCCAI only allows for natural numbers, our end points of remission &lt;3, partial remission ≤5, and response (SCCAI drop ≥2) are equivalent to these cutoffs.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28142-28338" id="S195" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Of the 24 study centers, 9 had &lt;4 patients and an additional 7 centers had &lt;8 patients, and this explains a certain deviation from a better balance between study arms (N varies between 35 and 41).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28339-28469" id="S196" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This, however, is not an issue because statistical tests are fitted more to simple randomization than to restricted randomization.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28478-28545" id="S197" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The randomization ratio was 1:1:1:1 with blocks of four per center.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28546-28749" id="S198" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This could mean a potential limited bias in case of the premature unblinding of a patient, as the investigators might draw conclusions concerning the treatment of the remaining patients at their centers.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28750-28831" id="S199" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In an isolated occurrence, a patient was accidentally unblinded by a study nurse.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28832-28996" id="S200" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">As the investigators were completely uninformed regarding the above-described packaging strategy, it is highly unlikely that this could influence the study outcome.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="28997-29104" id="S201" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A randomization ratio with blocks of eight would have been preferable, but it was financially not feasible.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29113-29178" id="S202" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Some authors expect a two-sided P value for the primary analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29179-29343" id="S203" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A one-sided P value, however, is often used in regulatory superiority studies with a stricter significance level of P=0.025 that equals a two-sided P value of 0.05.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29344-29426" id="S204" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Inferiority to placebo was not assumed, as previous studies had shown superiority.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29427-29608" id="S205" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All presented P values are two sided; only the P value for the primary analysis is presented as both one and two sided to facilitate the comparison with the stricter limit of 0.025.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29617-29676" id="S206" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Fecal calprotectin is an essential marker in UC at present.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29677-29789" id="S207" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">During the planning phase of the study, however, it was not established and was included into the running study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29790-29872" id="S208" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">As the study progressed so fast, the resulting data are too little to be analyzed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29895-29905" id="S209" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Conclusion</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29914-29983" id="S210" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">There is a pressing need for treatment alternatives in refractory UC.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="29984-30183" id="S211" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The goal of the study with the a priori defined primary end point of changes in disease activity was reached: the disease activity score dropped significantly under 3.2 g LT-02 compared with placebo.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30184-30229" id="S212" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Moreover, the drug was found to be very safe.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30230-30456" id="S213" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Although the improvement of the disease activity in the lower doses (0.8 and 1.6 g LT-02) was not statistically significant compared with placebo, the highest dose was effective and is intended for the planned pivotal studies.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30465-30704" id="S214" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The treatment effects of modified release PC appear to correlate with the shift of paradigm from immunological disorder to mucosal barrier dysfunction that has taken place in our understanding of inflammatory bowel disease in recent years.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30705-30795" id="S215" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Our findings could possibly further the treatment and understanding of ulcerative colitis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30819-30835" id="S216">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Study Highlights</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30860-30871" id="S217">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Back matter</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="30879-31400" id="S218" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We thank the following people for their help in recruiting and managing study patients in Germany: Sabine Stoffels, Annika Braun, and Robert Ehehalt (Heidelberg); Susanna Nikolaus, Tanja Kühbacher, Dörthe Schuldt, and Johannes Bethge (Kiel); Jana Berthold (Ulm); Bernd Bokemeyer (Minden); Sven and Sigrid Gehrke (Baden Baden); Babett Holler and Niels Teich (Leipzig); Stefanie Howaldt (Hamburg); Frank Lammert and Marc Dauer (Homburg); Christian Maaser (Lüneburg); Max Reinshagen (Braunschweig); Andreas Stallmach (Jena).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="31401-31638" id="S219" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We also thank Remigijus Garalevicius, Gediminas Kiudelis, Gintautas Radziunas, Romualdas Jurgutis, Laimas Jonaitis, and Gediminas Kiudelis (Lithuania); Adrian Goldis, Amelita Tirnaveanu, Christian Banciu, and Claudia Iacobescu (Romania).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="31639-31713" id="S220" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We thank Heather Karner and Janet Collins for proofreading the manuscript.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="31714-31810" id="S221" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We also thank Dr Michael Vieth from Bayreuth Hospital for providing the histological evaluation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="31811-31920" id="S222" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Pierrel Research (CRO) was responsible for the planning, organization, and statistical analyses of the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="31921-32113" id="S223" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">After unblinding the study, Winfried Koch verified the primary and secondary analyses and provided additional statistical support for the publication; he contributed to the statistics section.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32135-32143" id="S224" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Appendix</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32175-32216" id="S225" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Guarantor of the article: Max Karner, MD.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32223-32528" id="S226" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Specific author contributions: M.K. was the principal investigator of the study; he helped in the planning and conduct of the trial and prepared the manuscript; he had full access to all of the data in the study and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32529-32643" id="S227" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A.K., J.S., S.S., G.v.B., P.U., C.S., L.K., and I.D. were the site investigators of the most active study centers.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32644-32789" id="S228" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">F.Z. and G.K. are representatives of Lipid Therapeutics (sponsor), Heidelberg, Germany, and helped in the planning and organization of the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32790-32896" id="S229" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">W.S. is the inventor of mrPC; he helped in the study design and prepared the manuscript together with M.K.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="32903-33105" id="S230" selection="25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Financial support: Lipid Therapeutics (Heidelberg, Germany) is the sponsor of the study and financed the conduct of the study, the CRO, the second statistician, as well as the Data Monitoring Committee.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33106-33242" id="S231" selection="25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The investigators themselves did not receive money from the sponsor, but the study centers were reimbursed for their work with patients.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33243-33311" id="S232" selection="25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study sponsor helped plan the study design and financed the CRO.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33312-33431" id="S233" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The CRO, but not the sponsor, managed the conduct of the study, performed the study analyses, and interpreted the data.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33432-33529" id="S234" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The sponsor was neither involved in the data collection nor in the preparation of the manuscript.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33536-33671" id="S235" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Potential competing interests: M.K. was reimbursed for his costs to present the study data at a national and an international congress.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33672-33761" id="S236" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A.K., J.S., S.S., G.B., P.U., C.S., L.K., and I.D. had no potential conflict of interest.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33762-33811" id="S237" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">F.Z. and G.K. are representatives of the sponsor.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33812-33912" id="S238" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The adult and independent children of W.S. hold the patent for modified release phosphatidylcholine.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="33913-34010" id="S239" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">W.S., F.Z., and G.K. were not involved in patient recruitment, conduct, or analyses of the study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="34011-34209" id="S240" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Moreover, F.Z. and G.K., as representatives of the sponsor, were not involved in the preparation, review, or approval of the manuscript, nor in the decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</text>
    </sentence>
    <section textSpan="0-172" title="Title" titleSpan="0-5"/>
    <section textSpan="173-2624" title="Abstract" titleSpan="173-181">
        <section textSpan="191-543" title="OBJECTIVES:" titleSpan="202-213"/>
        <section textSpan="552-1281" title="METHODS:" titleSpan="563-571"/>
        <section textSpan="1290-2207" title="RESULTS:" titleSpan="1301-1309"/>
        <section textSpan="2216-2443" title="CONCLUSIONS:" titleSpan="2227-2239"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="2630-4803" title="INTRODUCTION" titleSpan="2637-2649"/>
    <section textSpan="4808-17001" title="METHODS" titleSpan="4815-4822">
        <section textSpan="10351-11851" title="Precautions against bias" titleSpan="10360-10384"/>
        <section textSpan="11858-13660" title="Outcomes" titleSpan="11867-11875"/>
        <section textSpan="13667-16996" title="Statistics" titleSpan="13676-13686"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="17006-22135" title="RESULTS" titleSpan="17013-17020">
        <section textSpan="18764-20856" title="Efficacy results" titleSpan="18773-18789"/>
        <section textSpan="20863-21839" title="Safety results" titleSpan="20872-20886"/>
        <section textSpan="21846-22130" title="Follow-up" titleSpan="21855-21864"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="22140-30807" title="DISCUSSION" titleSpan="22147-22157">
        <section textSpan="25745-29879" title="Limitations" titleSpan="25754-25765"/>
        <section textSpan="29886-30802" title="Conclusion" titleSpan="29895-29905"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="30812-30855" title="Study Highlights" titleSpan="30819-30835"/>
    <section textSpan="30860-34215" title="Back matter" titleSpan="30860-30871"/>
</document>
