<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<document id="PMC4145444" note="">
    <text xml:space="preserve">Title
Vitamin D treatment in calcium-deficiency rickets: a randomised controlled trial
Abstract

        
          Objective
          To determine whether children with calcium-deficiency rickets have a better response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium than with calcium alone.
        
        
          Design
          Randomised controlled trial.
        
        
          Setting
          Jos University Teaching Hospital, Jos, Nigeria.
        
        
          Population
          Nigerian children with active rickets treated with calcium carbonate as limestone (approximately 938 mg elemental calcium twice daily) were, in addition, randomised to receive either oral vitamin D2 50 000 IU (Ca+D, n=44) or placebo (Ca, n=28) monthly for 24 weeks.
        
        
          Main outcome measure
          Achievement of a 10-point radiographic severity score ≤1.5 and serum alkaline phosphatase ≤350 U/L.
        
        
          Results
          The median (range) age of enrolled children was 46 (15–102) months, and baseline characteristics were similar in the two groups. Mean (±SD) 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) was 30.2±13.2 nmol/L at baseline, and 29 (43%) had values &lt;30 nmol/L. Baseline alkaline phosphatase and radiographic scores were unrelated to vitamin D status. Of the 68 children (94% of original cohort) who completed 24 weeks of treatment, 29 (67%) in the Ca+D group and 11 (44%) in the Ca group achieved the primary outcome (p=0.06). Baseline 25(OH)D did not alter treatment group effects (p=0.99 for interaction). At the end of 24 weeks, 25(OH)D values were 55.4±17.0 nmol/L and 37.9±20.0 nmol/L in the Ca+D and Ca groups, respectively, (p&lt;0.001). In the Ca+D and Ca groups, the final 25(OH)D concentration was greater in those who achieved the primary outcome (56.4±17.2 nmol/L) than in those who did not (37.7±18.5 nmol/L, p&lt;0.001).
        
        
          Conclusions
          In children with calcium-deficiency rickets, there is a trend for vitamin D to improve the response to treatment with calcium carbonate as limestone, independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations.
        
        
          Trial registration number
          ClinicalTrials.gov NCT00949832.
        
      


    
      
        What is known about this topic?
      
       Nutritional rickets in most Nigerian children results from inadequate dietary calcium intake and responds to calcium supplementation.Children with inadequate calcium intake may have greater vitamin D requirements.
    
    
      
        What this study adds?
      
       Vitamin D in addition to treatment with calcium carbonate as limestone facilitates more rapid healing of rickets in children with calcium-deficiency rickets.The response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium was independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations.A greater increase in serum 25(OH)D concentration over the course of treatment was predictive of successful healing of rickets.
    
    
      Introduction
      Nutritional rickets in most Nigerian children results from inadequate dietary calcium intake, rather than vitamin D deficiency.1 However, vitamin D requirements and its metabolism in children with dietary calcium-deficiency rickets have not been adequately explored. Children with calcium-deficiency rickets have elevated serum 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D (1,25(OH)2D) values, which nearly doubles in response to a single oral dose of vitamin D.2 3 This increase in 1,25(OH)2D in children with calcium-deficiency rickets is suggestive of increased vitamin D requirements and a relative vitamin D deficiency, despite 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) values being greater than those generally considered indicative of deficiency.4
      In a randomised controlled trial, we found that treatment with vitamin D alone was less effective in healing rickets than treatment with calcium or calcium in combination with vitamin D.1 The primary outcome of the trial was the combined endpoint of radiographic healing and normalisation of serum alkaline phosphatase, and this outcome did not differ between the groups that received calcium with or without vitamin D. When compared with treatment with calcium alone, the combination of calcium and vitamin D resulted in a more rapid initial decline in alkaline phosphatase and improvement in radiographic score. Although vitamin D status, as measured by serum 25(OH)D, improved during treatment with calcium alone, the rise in 25(OH)D and the decline in 1,25(OH)2D were greater when calcium was combined with vitamin D than with calcium alone.
      The objective of this randomised controlled trial was to compare the response of rickets to calcium treatment as limestone with and without vitamin D supplementation.
    
    
      Methods
      
        Subjects
        Children with active rickets were identified using radiographs of the wrists and the knees from among children who presented with leg deformities to the primary care setting of the Family Medicine Department of the Jos University Teaching Hospital in the geographic centre of Nigeria (10° north latitude). Children were eligible for enrolment if they had a radiographic score of at least 2.5 on a validated 10-point scoring method that assessed the severity of rickets in the growth plates of the distal radius and ulna and around the knee.5 Approval for the study was obtained from the Ethical Committee of the Jos University Teaching Hospital and the Institutional Review Board of Mayo Clinic, and written informed consent was obtained from a parent of each enrolled child.
        Data were collected regarding symptoms of rickets, the frequency and quantity of dairy product intake, and usual sunlight exposure. The percentage of unclothed skin at enrolment was estimated with a Lund and Browder age-related burn chart. Standing height was measured with a wall-mounted stadiometer. Two 24-h dietary recalls were obtained on separate days to determine energy, phosphorus and calcium intake. Energy and mineral intakes were calculated using food composition tables for African foods.6–8 Weight was measured with a hanging weighing scale. Anthropometric z-scores were calculated with Epi Info 3.2.2 (CDC, Atlanta, Georgia, USA). All children were examined for clinical signs of rickets.
        Dual energy X-ray absorptiometry of the left distal and proximal 1/3 forearm was performed by a single investigator (TDT) with a portable densitometer (Norland pDEXA, Model 476A110). The densitometer had a short-term in vivo precision of 6.4% for areal bone density at the distal radius and ulna, and 7.2% at the proximal 1/3 radius and ulna, and a long-term in vitro precision of 1.1%.
      
      
        Intervention
        All children were treated with calcium carbonate as powdered limestone. Powdered limestone was locally available at a much lower cost than calcium tablets. The content of elemental calcium in 1.0 g of limestone was 268 mg (courtesy of Michael Gruzak, USDA/ARS Children's Nutrition Research Center, Houston, Texas, USA). Samples of limestone had no toxic concentrations of heavy metals. One level teaspoon of powdered limestone (approximately 3.5 g=938 mg of elemental calcium) was mixed with the child's food or porridge twice daily. Enrolled children were randomised by coin toss (performed by TDT) to receive under direct observation either oral vitamin D2 as 50 000 IU (ergocalciferol; Pliva, Inc., East Hanover, New Jersey) once every 4 weeks (Ca+D group) or placebo, which was a single vitamin B complex tablet, once every 4 weeks (Ca group) for 24 weeks.
        Subjects returned every 4 weeks for their supplements and assessment of adverse events. The weight of limestone remaining at each visit was recorded to assess adherence. Height, weight, venous blood, wrist and knee radiographs, and forearm bone density measurements were obtained at baseline and at 12 and 24 weeks after enrolment. Serum samples were stored at −20°C until transported frozen to the Mayo Clinic for analysis. Serum calcium, phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase and albumin were measured with standard methods. Serum 25(OH)D was measured by isotope-dilution liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS).9 Unless otherwise indicated by subscript notation for individual metabolites, 25(OH)D refers to the total concentrations of 25(OH)D2 and 25(OH)D3. Concentrations of 25(OH)D below the limit of detection (5 nmol/L for 25(OH)D3 and 10 nmol/L for 25(OH)D2) were designated as zero for the data analysis.
      
      
        Statistical analysis
        The primary outcome was the combined attainment of a radiographic score of 1.5 or less and a serum alkaline phosphatase concentration of 350 U/L or less. All radiographs were scored independently by two of the authors (TDT and PRF) and the mean score was used for analysis. Based on the primary outcome measures of radiographic score and serum alkaline phosphatase values and SDs based on previous studies (1.6 for radiographic score and 150 U/L in alkaline phosphatase), 40 subjects in each treatment group would provide 80% power and 95% CI to detect a difference between groups of 1.0 in final radiographic score and 100 U/L in alkaline phosphatase.
        Data analysis was performed with Excel 2003 (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, Washington, USA) and JMP V.9.0.1 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, North Carolina, USA). Unless otherwise noted, means and SDs are reported for continuous variables with normal distributions, and medians are reported for non-normally distributed variables. A paired t-test was used to compare values of continuous normally distributed variables with baseline values, and an unpaired t-test was used to compare values of continuous variables between groups. The Wilcoxon test was used to compare non-normally distributed variables. Logistic regression was used to assess the effect of treatment group on the primary outcome while controlling for baseline group differences and to test for interactions between variables. p Values less than 0.05 were considered significant.
      
    
    
      Results
      A total of 254 children presented with leg deformities, and 72 subjects with radiographically active rickets were enrolled between February 2004 and November 2006 (figure 1). The baseline characteristics at enrolment are shown in table 1. Because of the nature of coin toss randomisation, the number of subjects in the Ca+D group (n=44) was greater than the number in the Ca group (n=28). Unlike classical vitamin D-deficiency rickets, all children were over the age of 1 year at presentation and most had regular sun exposure. Dietary calcium intake was uniformly low, reflecting minimal dairy product intake. Their calcium intakes were well below the Institute of Medicine's estimated average daily requirements of 500 mg and 800 mg for children 1–3 years of age and 4–8 years of age, respectively.4 Children's heights were significantly stunted, in part reflecting their leg deformities, but their relatively normal weight for height and serum albumin did not indicate acute malnutrition.
       Table 1 Baseline characteristics of groups at randomisation* 
       Figure 1  
      The baseline mean (±SD) 25(OH)D concentration was 30.2±13.2 nmol/L, and 29 (40%) had values below 30 nmol/L. Baseline alkaline phosphatase and radiographic scores were unrelated to 25(OH)D concentrations. Baseline dairy product intake was not significantly associated with height for age (r=0.19), weight for height (r=0.02), serum calcium (r=0.07) or 25(OH)D concentrations (r=−0.05). However, total dietary calcium intake was positively related to weight for height (r=0.29; p=0.01), 25(OH)D concentration (r=0.24; p=0.04) and total energy intake (r=0.59; p&lt;0.001).
      Of those enrolled, 68 (94%) completed 24 weeks of treatment. The median adherence to calcium supplementation, based on the weight of unused limestone, was 99% in the Ca group and 96% in the Ca+D group (p=0.54). Alkaline phosphatase values and radiographic scores improved in both groups (figures 2 and 3). In an analysis of alkaline phosphatase values, adjusted for baseline values, mean values were marginally lower in the Ca+D group than the Ca group at 12 weeks (p=0.06) but not at 24 weeks (p=0.40). Similarly, adjusted mean radiographic scores were lower in the Ca+D group at 12 weeks (p=0.01) but not at 24 weeks (p=0.12).
       Figure 2  
       Figure 3  
      At the end of 24 weeks, 29 (67%; 95% CI 53% to 80%) in the Ca+D group and 11 (44%; 95% CI 27% to 63%) in the Ca group achieved the primary combined outcome of radiographic and alkaline phosphatase endpoints, and this difference was marginally significant (p=0.06). At the intermediate time point of 12 weeks, 11 (26%) in the Ca+D group and 1 (4.2%) in the Ca group had achieved the combined outcome (p=0.03).
      In a logistic regression analysis that controlled for baseline values of alkaline phosphatase, radiographic score, serum 25(OH)D and height for age, treatment with calcium plus vitamin D was significantly superior to treatment with calcium alone (table 2). Interestingly, baseline 25(OH)D concentration was not predictive of a response to vitamin D, as there was no interaction of treatment group with baseline 25(OH)D (p=0.42 for interaction).
       Table 2 Logistic regression analysis of factors at enrolment predictive of primary outcome 
      At the end of 24 weeks, mean serum calcium values increased similarly in the two treatment groups, and mean 25(OH)D values had increased to 55.4±17.0 nmol/L and 37.9±20.0 nmol/L in the Ca+D and the Ca groups, respectively, (p&lt;0.001; figure 4). In the Ca+D and Ca groups, the response to treatment was associated with an increase in 25(OH)D concentration. Of the 10 subjects with 25(OH)D &lt;30 nmol/L at 24 weeks, two (20%) attained the primary outcome compared with 66% of those with 25(OH)D ≥30 nmol/L (p=0.006). The final 25(OH)D concentration was greater in those who achieved the primary outcome than in those who did not (56.4±17.2 nmol/L vs 37.7±18.5 nmol/L, respectively, p&lt;0.001). The increase in height over the course of treatment was significantly related to the final 25(OH)D concentration (r=0.28; p=0.02).
       Figure 4  
      The incremental increase in the distal forearm bone mineral content in the Ca group (least squares mean increase 0.093 g) was nearly twice that of the Ca+D group (least squares mean increase 0.053 g; p=0.02) in a model adjusting for baseline bone mineral content and height. However, the increase in proximal 1/3 forearm bone mineral in the Ca group (least squares mean increase 0.130 g) was similar to that of the Ca+D group (least squares mean increase 0.109 g; p=0.22). The increase in distal and proximal 1/3 bone mineral content was unrelated to treatment response, as assessed by the combined outcome of radiographic and alkaline phosphatase endpoints.
    
    
      Discussion
      We found that vitamin D facilitates more rapid healing, improves vitamin D status and had a marginally significant effect on recovery at the end of 6 months in children with calcium-deficiency rickets treated with calcium carbonate as limestone. The response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium was independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations. However, a response to treatment with either calcium or calcium in combination with vitamin D was associated with a greater increase in 25(OH)D concentrations over the period of therapy than in those who did not respond as well.
      In a previous study in this population, we found no difference in the primary outcome between groups that received calcium with or without vitamin D, but there was a more rapid initial decline in alkaline phosphatase in the group that received the combination of vitamin D and calcium.1 In comparing the results of the two studies, we noted that 61% of the calcium group in the earlier study achieved the primary outcome compared with only 44% in the current study. Baseline characteristics of children with rickets were similar, and we used the same combined endpoint in both studies. However, several differences between the interventions in the two studies may account for the disparate results. In the previous study, children were treated with calcium as calcium carbonate tablets and vitamin D3 as 600 000 IU injections every 3 months, whereas in the present study, we used limestone with a greater dose of elemental calcium and vitamin D2 50 000 IU given orally every 4 weeks. Calcium as limestone may be less bioavailable than calcium in tablets of calcium carbonate. Because the limestone was mixed with food or porridge, children who did not finish their food would not have had a complete dose. This may explain, in part, the difference in outcomes between the calcium groups in the two trials. The primary outcome in the Ca+D group was achieved in 67% of subjects in this study compared with 58% in our prior study. Compared with our earlier study, the superior outcome of the Ca+D group in this study may reflect an effect of dosing of vitamin D every 4 weeks as opposed to a larger dose administered every 12 weeks. Effective healing of rickets in the Ca+D group indicates that the bioavailability of calcium from limestone was sufficient when vitamin D status was optimised. Limestone can be used as an inexpensive source of calcium in low-income countries where rickets is prevalent.
      In comparison, a recent trial in 67 children with nutritional rickets in India compared treatment with calcium, vitamin D or the combination for 12 weeks.10 Normal serum alkaline phosphatase and complete radiological healing were observed in 12%, 16% and 50% of subjects in the calcium, vitamin D and combination groups, respectively. The Indian children were younger (median age 14 months) than children in our trial, but baseline 25(OH)D values (median 34 nmol/L) were similar. The authors concluded that treatment of children with nutritional rickets and low dietary calcium intakes responded better to the combination of vitamin D and calcium than to calcium alone. Their trial did not examine healing of rickets beyond 12 weeks, the relationship of 25(OH)D with treatment response or the effect of treatment on bone density.
      It is not clear why vitamin D enhances healing of rickets in children with calcium-deficiency rickets, even in those with adequate vitamin D status, as we have previously shown excellent intestinal calcium absorption without D supplementation. Vitamin D does not improve the already maximal fractional calcium absorption in Nigerian children with rickets, even in those with low serum 25(OH)D concentrations.11 Studies in adults indicate that intestinal calcium absorption is not significantly reduced until 25(OH)D concentrations are ≤10 nmol/L.12 Current evidence indicates that vitamin D requirements are greater when dietary calcium intakes are low.3 13 This is consistent with our findings in Nigerian children with calcium-deficiency rickets, who demonstrate a marked increase in 1,25(OH)2D in response to vitamin D administration.2 3 These findings suggest that vitamin D metabolites may have a direct or indirect effect on bone mineralisation by mechanisms other than calcium absorption.14 Vitamin D also promotes intestinal phosphorus absorption and mediates phosphorus metabolism, which may also be critical for healing of the rickets.
      Surprisingly, the increase in bone density of the distal radius and ulna was greater in the Ca group than in the Ca+D group. Nutritional rickets impairs endochondral ossification at the growth plates, and the growth plates of the radius and ulna are located distally near the wrist. We have previously demonstrated that calcium supplementation increases forearm bone density in young Nigerian children,15 but this increase was not sustained after withdrawal of calcium supplementation.16
      One of the limitations of our study was that we did not attain our target enrolment of 40 subjects in each group before the study concluded. The power of our sample size to detect the observed difference in the primary outcome (67% vs 44%) with 95% CI was 46%. However, this lack of power does not affect the conclusions related to our findings that were statistically significant. Coin toss randomisation led to unequal group sizes, but this method of simple randomisation is less error prone than restricted randomisation, because it is entirely unpredictable. However, it is more likely to generate baseline imbalances between the characteristics of the treatment groups, which we did not observe in our trial. Trials that are numerically imbalanced are still scientifically sound, and loss of power occurs only when the imbalance is much greater than 2:1.17
      Even children with nutritional rickets resulting from insufficient dietary calcium benefit from vitamin D supplementation in addition to calcium to promote more rapid healing. Limestone can be used as an inexpensive source of calcium in low-income countries.
    
  

Back matter

      
        Contributors: TDT, PRF and JMP were responsible for conception and design. TDT acquired the data and performed the data analysis. All authors interpreted the data and critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content. TDT obtained funding, drafted the manuscript and is the guarantor. TDT affirms that the manuscript is an honest, accurate and transparent account of the study being reported; that no important aspects of the study have been omitted and that any discrepancies from the study as planned and registered have been explained.
      
      
        Funding: This study was supported by Grant Number 1 UL1 RR024150 from the National Center for Research Resources (NCRR), a component of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and the NIH Roadmap for Medical Research. Its contents are solely the responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official view of NCRR or NIH. Information on NCRR is available at http://www.ncrr.nih.gov/. Information on Reengineering the Clinical Research Enterprise can be obtained from http://nihroadmap.nih.gov. The study sponsor had no role in study design and the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and the writing of the article and the decision to submit it for publication.
      
      
        Competing interests: All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form at http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: TDT reports grants from National Center for Research Resources, during the conduct of the study; personal fees from Biomedical Systems, outside the submitted work; no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work. PRF and JMP have nothing to disclose.
      
      
        Ethics approval: This project was approved by the Mayo Clinic Institutional Review Board and the Jos University Teaching Hospital Ethical Committee.
      
      
        Provenance and peer review: Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</text>
    <sentence charOffset="0-5" id="S1">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Title</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6-86" id="S2" selection="1a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Vitamin D treatment in calcium-deficiency rickets: a randomised controlled trial</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="87-95" id="S3">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Abstract</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="116-125" id="S4" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Objective</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="136-285" id="S5" selection="1b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">To determine whether children with calcium-deficiency rickets have a better response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium than with calcium alone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="314-320" id="S6" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Design</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="331-359" id="S7" selection="3a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Randomised controlled trial.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="388-395" id="S8" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Setting</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="406-453" id="S9" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Jos University Teaching Hospital, Jos, Nigeria.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="482-492" id="S10" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Population</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="503-768" id="S11" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Nigerian children with active rickets treated with calcium carbonate as limestone (approximately 938 mg elemental calcium twice daily) were, in addition, randomised to receive either oral vitamin D2 50 000 IU (Ca+D, n=44) or placebo (Ca, n=28) monthly for 24 weeks.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="797-817" id="S12" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Main outcome measure</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="828-927" id="S13" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Achievement of a 10-point radiographic severity score ≤1.5 and serum alkaline phosphatase ≤350 U/L.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="956-963" id="S14" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Results</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="974-1102" id="S15" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The median (range) age of enrolled children was 46 (15–102) months, and baseline characteristics were similar in the two groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1103-1303" id="S16" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Mean (±SD) 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) was 30.2±13.2 nmol/L at baseline, and 29 (43%) had values &lt;30 nmol/L. Baseline alkaline phosphatase and radiographic scores were unrelated to vitamin D status.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1304-1479" id="S17" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Of the 68 children (94% of original cohort) who completed 24 weeks of treatment, 29 (67%) in the Ca+D group and 11 (44%) in the Ca group achieved the primary outcome (p=0.06).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1480-1560" id="S18" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Baseline 25(OH)D did not alter treatment group effects (p=0.99 for interaction).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1561-1694" id="S19" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the end of 24 weeks, 25(OH)D values were 55.4±17.0 nmol/L and 37.9±20.0 nmol/L in the Ca+D and Ca groups, respectively, (p&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1695-1881" id="S20" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the Ca+D and Ca groups, the final 25(OH)D concentration was greater in those who achieved the primary outcome (56.4±17.2 nmol/L) than in those who did not (37.7±18.5 nmol/L, p&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1910-1921" id="S21" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Conclusions</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="1932-2129" id="S22" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In children with calcium-deficiency rickets, there is a trend for vitamin D to improve the response to treatment with calcium carbonate as limestone, independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2158-2183" id="S23" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Trial registration number</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2194-2225" id="S24" selection="23">
        <text xml:space="preserve">ClinicalTrials.gov NCT00949832.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2264-2295" id="S25" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">What is known about this topic?</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2310-2523" id="S26" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Nutritional rickets in most Nigerian children results from inadequate dietary calcium intake and responds to calcium supplementation.Children with inadequate calcium intake may have greater vitamin D requirements.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2549-2570" id="S27" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">What this study adds?</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2585-2973" id="S28" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Vitamin D in addition to treatment with calcium carbonate as limestone facilitates more rapid healing of rickets in children with calcium-deficiency rickets.The response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium was independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations.A greater increase in serum 25(OH)D concentration over the course of treatment was predictive of successful healing of rickets.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="2990-3002" id="S29">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Introduction</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3009-3137" id="S30" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Nutritional rickets in most Nigerian children results from inadequate dietary calcium intake, rather than vitamin D deficiency.1</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3138-3275" id="S31" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, vitamin D requirements and its metabolism in children with dietary calcium-deficiency rickets have not been adequately explored.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3276-3453" id="S32" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Children with calcium-deficiency rickets have elevated serum 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D (1,25(OH)2D) values, which nearly doubles in response to a single oral dose of vitamin D.2 3</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3454-3730" id="S33" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This increase in 1,25(OH)2D in children with calcium-deficiency rickets is suggestive of increased vitamin D requirements and a relative vitamin D deficiency, despite 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25(OH)D) values being greater than those generally considered indicative of deficiency.4</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3737-3924" id="S34" selection="2a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In a randomised controlled trial, we found that treatment with vitamin D alone was less effective in healing rickets than treatment with calcium or calcium in combination with vitamin D.1</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="3925-4350" id="S35" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary outcome of the trial was the combined endpoint of radiographic healing and normalisation of serum alkaline phosphatase, and this outcome did not differ between the groups that received calcium with or without vitamin D. When compared with treatment with calcium alone, the combination of calcium and vitamin D resulted in a more rapid initial decline in alkaline phosphatase and improvement in radiographic score.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4351-4582" id="S36" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Although vitamin D status, as measured by serum 25(OH)D, improved during treatment with calcium alone, the rise in 25(OH)D and the decline in 1,25(OH)2D were greater when calcium was combined with vitamin D than with calcium alone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4589-4755" id="S37" selection="2b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The objective of this randomised controlled trial was to compare the response of rickets to calcium treatment as limestone with and without vitamin D supplementation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4772-4779" id="S38">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Methods</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4795-4803" id="S39" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Subjects</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="4812-5117" id="S40" selection="4a,4b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Children with active rickets were identified using radiographs of the wrists and the knees from among children who presented with leg deformities to the primary care setting of the Family Medicine Department of the Jos University Teaching Hospital in the geographic centre of Nigeria (10° north latitude).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5118-5353" id="S41" selection="4a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Children were eligible for enrolment if they had a radiographic score of at least 2.5 on a validated 10-point scoring method that assessed the severity of rickets in the growth plates of the distal radius and ulna and around the knee.5</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5354-5587" id="S42" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Approval for the study was obtained from the Ethical Committee of the Jos University Teaching Hospital and the Institutional Review Board of Mayo Clinic, and written informed consent was obtained from a parent of each enrolled child.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5596-5727" id="S43" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data were collected regarding symptoms of rickets, the frequency and quantity of dairy product intake, and usual sunlight exposure.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5728-5835" id="S44" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The percentage of unclothed skin at enrolment was estimated with a Lund and Browder age-related burn chart.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5836-5897" id="S45" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Standing height was measured with a wall-mounted stadiometer.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="5898-6005" id="S46" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Two 24-h dietary recalls were obtained on separate days to determine energy, phosphorus and calcium intake.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6006-6100" id="S47" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Energy and mineral intakes were calculated using food composition tables for African foods.6–8</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6101-6151" id="S48" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Weight was measured with a hanging weighing scale.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6152-6241" id="S49" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Anthropometric z-scores were calculated with Epi Info 3.2.2 (CDC, Atlanta, Georgia, USA).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6242-6299" id="S50" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All children were examined for clinical signs of rickets.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6308-6490" id="S51" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Dual energy X-ray absorptiometry of the left distal and proximal 1/3 forearm was performed by a single investigator (TDT) with a portable densitometer (Norland pDEXA, Model 476A110).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6491-6694" id="S52" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The densitometer had a short-term in vivo precision of 6.4% for areal bone density at the distal radius and ulna, and 7.2% at the proximal 1/3 radius and ulna, and a long-term in vitro precision of 1.1%.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6717-6729" id="S53" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Intervention</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6738-6809" id="S54" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All children were treated with calcium carbonate as powdered limestone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6810-6893" id="S55" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Powdered limestone was locally available at a much lower cost than calcium tablets.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="6894-7057" id="S56" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The content of elemental calcium in 1.0 g of limestone was 268 mg (courtesy of Michael Gruzak, USDA/ARS Children's Nutrition Research Center, Houston, Texas, USA).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7058-7123" id="S57" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Samples of limestone had no toxic concentrations of heavy metals.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7124-7271" id="S58" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">One level teaspoon of powdered limestone (approximately 3.5 g=938 mg of elemental calcium) was mixed with the child's food or porridge twice daily.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7272-7598" id="S59" selection="8b,10">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Enrolled children were randomised by coin toss (performed by TDT) to receive under direct observation either oral vitamin D2 as 50 000 IU (ergocalciferol; Pliva, Inc., East Hanover, New Jersey) once every 4 weeks (Ca+D group) or placebo, which was a single vitamin B complex tablet, once every 4 weeks (Ca group) for 24 weeks.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7607-7694" id="S60" selection="5">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Subjects returned every 4 weeks for their supplements and assessment of adverse events.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7695-7776" id="S61" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The weight of limestone remaining at each visit was recorded to assess adherence.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7777-7938" id="S62" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Height, weight, venous blood, wrist and knee radiographs, and forearm bone density measurements were obtained at baseline and at 12 and 24 weeks after enrolment.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="7939-8031" id="S63" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Serum samples were stored at −20°C until transported frozen to the Mayo Clinic for analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8032-8128" id="S64" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Serum calcium, phosphorus, alkaline phosphatase and albumin were measured with standard methods.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8129-8235" id="S65" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Serum 25(OH)D was measured by isotope-dilution liquid chromatography–tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS).9</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8236-8381" id="S66" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Unless otherwise indicated by subscript notation for individual metabolites, 25(OH)D refers to the total concentrations of 25(OH)D2 and 25(OH)D3.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8382-8534" id="S67" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Concentrations of 25(OH)D below the limit of detection (5 nmol/L for 25(OH)D3 and 10 nmol/L for 25(OH)D2) were designated as zero for the data analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8557-8577" id="S68" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Statistical analysis</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8586-8739" id="S69" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary outcome was the combined attainment of a radiographic score of 1.5 or less and a serum alkaline phosphatase concentration of 350 U/L or less.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8740-8859" id="S70" selection="6a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All radiographs were scored independently by two of the authors (TDT and PRF) and the mean score was used for analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="8860-9238" id="S71" selection="7a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Based on the primary outcome measures of radiographic score and serum alkaline phosphatase values and SDs based on previous studies (1.6 for radiographic score and 150 U/L in alkaline phosphatase), 40 subjects in each treatment group would provide 80% power and 95% CI to detect a difference between groups of 1.0 in final radiographic score and 100 U/L in alkaline phosphatase.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9247-9399" id="S72" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Data analysis was performed with Excel 2003 (Microsoft Corp., Redmond, Washington, USA) and JMP V.9.0.1 (SAS Institute Inc., Cary, North Carolina, USA).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9400-9567" id="S73" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Unless otherwise noted, means and SDs are reported for continuous variables with normal distributions, and medians are reported for non-normally distributed variables.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9568-9767" id="S74" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A paired t-test was used to compare values of continuous normally distributed variables with baseline values, and an unpaired t-test was used to compare values of continuous variables between groups.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9768-9841" id="S75" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The Wilcoxon test was used to compare non-normally distributed variables.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="9842-10030" id="S76" selection="12a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Logistic regression was used to assess the effect of treatment group on the primary outcome while controlling for baseline group differences and to test for interactions between variables.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10031-10083" id="S77" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">p Values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10107-10114" id="S78">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Results</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10121-10295" id="S79" selection="14a,13a,13b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">A total of 254 children presented with leg deformities, and 72 subjects with radiographically active rickets were enrolled between February 2004 and November 2006 (figure 1).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10296-10359" id="S80" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The baseline characteristics at enrolment are shown in table 1.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10360-10509" id="S81" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Because of the nature of coin toss randomisation, the number of subjects in the Ca+D group (n=44) was greater than the number in the Ca group (n=28).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10510-10648" id="S82" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Unlike classical vitamin D-deficiency rickets, all children were over the age of 1 year at presentation and most had regular sun exposure.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10649-10731" id="S83" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Dietary calcium intake was uniformly low, reflecting minimal dairy product intake.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10732-10922" id="S84" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Their calcium intakes were well below the Institute of Medicine's estimated average daily requirements of 500 mg and 800 mg for children 1–3 years of age and 4–8 years of age, respectively.4</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="10923-11112" id="S85" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Children's heights were significantly stunted, in part reflecting their leg deformities, but their relatively normal weight for height and serum albumin did not indicate acute malnutrition.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11120-11180" id="S86" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 1 Baseline characteristics of groups at randomisation*</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11189-11197" id="S87" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 1</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11206-11410" id="S88" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The baseline mean (±SD) 25(OH)D concentration was 30.2±13.2 nmol/L, and 29 (40%) had values below 30 nmol/L. Baseline alkaline phosphatase and radiographic scores were unrelated to 25(OH)D concentrations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11411-11591" id="S89" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Baseline dairy product intake was not significantly associated with height for age (r=0.19), weight for height (r=0.02), serum calcium (r=0.07) or 25(OH)D concentrations (r=−0.05).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11592-11773" id="S90" selection="15">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, total dietary calcium intake was positively related to weight for height (r=0.29; p=0.01), 25(OH)D concentration (r=0.24; p=0.04) and total energy intake (r=0.59; p&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11780-11840" id="S91" selection="16">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Of those enrolled, 68 (94%) completed 24 weeks of treatment.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11841-11990" id="S92" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The median adherence to calcium supplementation, based on the weight of unused limestone, was 99% in the Ca group and 96% in the Ca+D group (p=0.54).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="11991-12085" id="S93" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Alkaline phosphatase values and radiographic scores improved in both groups (figures 2 and 3).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12086-12283" id="S94" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In an analysis of alkaline phosphatase values, adjusted for baseline values, mean values were marginally lower in the Ca+D group than the Ca group at 12 weeks (p=0.06) but not at 24 weeks (p=0.40).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12284-12408" id="S95" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Similarly, adjusted mean radiographic scores were lower in the Ca+D group at 12 weeks (p=0.01) but not at 24 weeks (p=0.12).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12416-12424" id="S96" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 2</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12434-12442" id="S97" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 3</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12451-12715" id="S98" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the end of 24 weeks, 29 (67%; 95% CI 53% to 80%) in the Ca+D group and 11 (44%; 95% CI 27% to 63%) in the Ca group achieved the primary combined outcome of radiographic and alkaline phosphatase endpoints, and this difference was marginally significant (p=0.06).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12716-12859" id="S99" selection="17b">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the intermediate time point of 12 weeks, 11 (26%) in the Ca+D group and 1 (4.2%) in the Ca group had achieved the combined outcome (p=0.03).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="12866-13122" id="S100" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In a logistic regression analysis that controlled for baseline values of alkaline phosphatase, radiographic score, serum 25(OH)D and height for age, treatment with calcium plus vitamin D was significantly superior to treatment with calcium alone (table 2).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13123-13310" id="S101" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Interestingly, baseline 25(OH)D concentration was not predictive of a response to vitamin D, as there was no interaction of treatment group with baseline 25(OH)D (p=0.42 for interaction).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13318-13408" id="S102" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Table 2 Logistic regression analysis of factors at enrolment predictive of primary outcome</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13416-13659" id="S103" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">At the end of 24 weeks, mean serum calcium values increased similarly in the two treatment groups, and mean 25(OH)D values had increased to 55.4±17.0 nmol/L and 37.9±20.0 nmol/L in the Ca+D and the Ca groups, respectively, (p&lt;0.001; figure 4).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13660-13770" id="S104" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the Ca+D and Ca groups, the response to treatment was associated with an increase in 25(OH)D concentration.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13771-13927" id="S105" selection="18">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Of the 10 subjects with 25(OH)D &lt;30 nmol/L at 24 weeks, two (20%) attained the primary outcome compared with 66% of those with 25(OH)D ≥30 nmol/L (p=0.006).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="13928-14102" id="S106" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The final 25(OH)D concentration was greater in those who achieved the primary outcome than in those who did not (56.4±17.2 nmol/L vs 37.7±18.5 nmol/L, respectively, p&lt;0.001).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14103-14233" id="S107" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The increase in height over the course of treatment was significantly related to the final 25(OH)D concentration (r=0.28; p=0.02).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14241-14249" id="S108" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Figure 4</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14258-14532" id="S109" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The incremental increase in the distal forearm bone mineral content in the Ca group (least squares mean increase 0.093 g) was nearly twice that of the Ca+D group (least squares mean increase 0.053 g; p=0.02) in a model adjusting for baseline bone mineral content and height.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14533-14730" id="S110" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, the increase in proximal 1/3 forearm bone mineral in the Ca group (least squares mean increase 0.130 g) was similar to that of the Ca+D group (least squares mean increase 0.109 g; p=0.22).</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14731-14916" id="S111" selection="17a">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The increase in distal and proximal 1/3 bone mineral content was unrelated to treatment response, as assessed by the combined outcome of radiographic and alkaline phosphatase endpoints.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14933-14943" id="S112">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Discussion</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="14950-15195" id="S113" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We found that vitamin D facilitates more rapid healing, improves vitamin D status and had a marginally significant effect on recovery at the end of 6 months in children with calcium-deficiency rickets treated with calcium carbonate as limestone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15196-15300" id="S114" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The response to treatment with vitamin D and calcium was independent of baseline 25(OH)D concentrations.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15301-15529" id="S115" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, a response to treatment with either calcium or calcium in combination with vitamin D was associated with a greater increase in 25(OH)D concentrations over the period of therapy than in those who did not respond as well.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15536-15822" id="S116" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In a previous study in this population, we found no difference in the primary outcome between groups that received calcium with or without vitamin D, but there was a more rapid initial decline in alkaline phosphatase in the group that received the combination of vitamin D and calcium.1</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="15823-16001" id="S117" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In comparing the results of the two studies, we noted that 61% of the calcium group in the earlier study achieved the primary outcome compared with only 44% in the current study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16002-16121" id="S118" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Baseline characteristics of children with rickets were similar, and we used the same combined endpoint in both studies.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16122-16234" id="S119" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, several differences between the interventions in the two studies may account for the disparate results.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16235-16519" id="S120" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In the previous study, children were treated with calcium as calcium carbonate tablets and vitamin D3 as 600 000 IU injections every 3 months, whereas in the present study, we used limestone with a greater dose of elemental calcium and vitamin D2 50 000 IU given orally every 4 weeks.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16520-16611" id="S121" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Calcium as limestone may be less bioavailable than calcium in tablets of calcium carbonate.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16612-16741" id="S122" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Because the limestone was mixed with food or porridge, children who did not finish their food would not have had a complete dose.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16742-16841" id="S123" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This may explain, in part, the difference in outcomes between the calcium groups in the two trials.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16842-16963" id="S124" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The primary outcome in the Ca+D group was achieved in 67% of subjects in this study compared with 58% in our prior study.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="16964-17165" id="S125" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Compared with our earlier study, the superior outcome of the Ca+D group in this study may reflect an effect of dosing of vitamin D every 4 weeks as opposed to a larger dose administered every 12 weeks.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17166-17325" id="S126" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Effective healing of rickets in the Ca+D group indicates that the bioavailability of calcium from limestone was sufficient when vitamin D status was optimised.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17326-17435" id="S127" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Limestone can be used as an inexpensive source of calcium in low-income countries where rickets is prevalent.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17442-17598" id="S128" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">In comparison, a recent trial in 67 children with nutritional rickets in India compared treatment with calcium, vitamin D or the combination for 12 weeks.10</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17599-17776" id="S129" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Normal serum alkaline phosphatase and complete radiological healing were observed in 12%, 16% and 50% of subjects in the calcium, vitamin D and combination groups, respectively.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17777-17921" id="S130" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The Indian children were younger (median age 14 months) than children in our trial, but baseline 25(OH)D values (median 34 nmol/L) were similar.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="17922-18111" id="S131" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The authors concluded that treatment of children with nutritional rickets and low dietary calcium intakes responded better to the combination of vitamin D and calcium than to calcium alone.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18112-18271" id="S132" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Their trial did not examine healing of rickets beyond 12 weeks, the relationship of 25(OH)D with treatment response or the effect of treatment on bone density.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18278-18521" id="S133" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">It is not clear why vitamin D enhances healing of rickets in children with calcium-deficiency rickets, even in those with adequate vitamin D status, as we have previously shown excellent intestinal calcium absorption without D supplementation.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18522-18688" id="S134" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Vitamin D does not improve the already maximal fractional calcium absorption in Nigerian children with rickets, even in those with low serum 25(OH)D concentrations.11</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18689-18826" id="S135" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Studies in adults indicate that intestinal calcium absorption is not significantly reduced until 25(OH)D concentrations are ≤10 nmol/L.12</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18827-18935" id="S136" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Current evidence indicates that vitamin D requirements are greater when dietary calcium intakes are low.3 13</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="18936-19118" id="S137" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">This is consistent with our findings in Nigerian children with calcium-deficiency rickets, who demonstrate a marked increase in 1,25(OH)2D in response to vitamin D administration.2 3</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19119-19275" id="S138" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">These findings suggest that vitamin D metabolites may have a direct or indirect effect on bone mineralisation by mechanisms other than calcium absorption.14</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19276-19423" id="S139" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Vitamin D also promotes intestinal phosphorus absorption and mediates phosphorus metabolism, which may also be critical for healing of the rickets.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19430-19554" id="S140" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Surprisingly, the increase in bone density of the distal radius and ulna was greater in the Ca group than in the Ca+D group.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19555-19712" id="S141" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Nutritional rickets impairs endochondral ossification at the growth plates, and the growth plates of the radius and ulna are located distally near the wrist.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19713-19917" id="S142" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">We have previously demonstrated that calcium supplementation increases forearm bone density in young Nigerian children,15 but this increase was not sustained after withdrawal of calcium supplementation.16</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="19924-20064" id="S143" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">One of the limitations of our study was that we did not attain our target enrolment of 40 subjects in each group before the study concluded.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20065-20184" id="S144" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The power of our sample size to detect the observed difference in the primary outcome (67% vs 44%) with 95% CI was 46%.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20185-20305" id="S145" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, this lack of power does not affect the conclusions related to our findings that were statistically significant.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20306-20486" id="S146" selection="20">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Coin toss randomisation led to unequal group sizes, but this method of simple randomisation is less error prone than restricted randomisation, because it is entirely unpredictable.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20487-20637" id="S147" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">However, it is more likely to generate baseline imbalances between the characteristics of the treatment groups, which we did not observe in our trial.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20638-20785" id="S148" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Trials that are numerically imbalanced are still scientifically sound, and loss of power occurs only when the imbalance is much greater than 2:1.17</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20792-20967" id="S149" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Even children with nutritional rickets resulting from insufficient dietary calcium benefit from vitamin D supplementation in addition to calcium to promote more rapid healing.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="20968-21050" id="S150" selection="22">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Limestone can be used as an inexpensive source of calcium in low-income countries.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21060-21071" id="S151">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Back matter</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21088-21162" id="S152" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Contributors: TDT, PRF and JMP were responsible for conception and design.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21163-21217" id="S153" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">TDT acquired the data and performed the data analysis.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21218-21324" id="S154" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">All authors interpreted the data and critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21325-21391" id="S155" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">TDT obtained funding, drafted the manuscript and is the guarantor.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21392-21645" id="S156" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">TDT affirms that the manuscript is an honest, accurate and transparent account of the study being reported; that no important aspects of the study have been omitted and that any discrepancies from the study as planned and registered have been explained.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21668-21885" id="S157" selection="25">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Funding: This study was supported by Grant Number 1 UL1 RR024150 from the National Center for Research Resources (NCRR), a component of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) and the NIH Roadmap for Medical Research.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="21886-22010" id="S158" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Its contents are solely the responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily represent the official view of NCRR or NIH.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22011-22072" id="S159" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Information on NCRR is available at http://www.ncrr.nih.gov/.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22073-22182" id="S160" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Information on Reengineering the Clinical Research Enterprise can be obtained from http://nihroadmap.nih.gov.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22183-22363" id="S161" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">The study sponsor had no role in study design and the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and the writing of the article and the decision to submit it for publication.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22386-22781" id="S162" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Competing interests: All authors have completed the ICMJE uniform disclosure form at http://www.icmje.org/coi_disclosure.pdf and declare: TDT reports grants from National Center for Research Resources, during the conduct of the study; personal fees from Biomedical Systems, outside the submitted work; no other relationships or activities that could appear to have influenced the submitted work.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22782-22819" id="S163" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">PRF and JMP have nothing to disclose.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="22842-22990" id="S164" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Ethics approval: This project was approved by the Mayo Clinic Institutional Review Board and the Jos University Teaching Hospital Ethical Committee.</text>
    </sentence>
    <sentence charOffset="23013-23084" id="S165" selection="">
        <text xml:space="preserve">Provenance and peer review: Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</text>
    </sentence>
    <section textSpan="0-86" title="Title" titleSpan="0-5"/>
    <section textSpan="87-2242" title="Abstract" titleSpan="87-95">
        <section textSpan="105-294" title="Objective" titleSpan="116-125"/>
        <section textSpan="303-368" title="Design" titleSpan="314-320"/>
        <section textSpan="377-462" title="Setting" titleSpan="388-395"/>
        <section textSpan="471-777" title="Population" titleSpan="482-492"/>
        <section textSpan="786-936" title="Main outcome measure" titleSpan="797-817"/>
        <section textSpan="945-1890" title="Results" titleSpan="956-963"/>
        <section textSpan="1899-2138" title="Conclusions" titleSpan="1910-1921"/>
        <section textSpan="2147-2234" title="Trial registration number" titleSpan="2158-2183"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="2983-4760" title="Introduction" titleSpan="2990-3002"/>
    <section textSpan="4765-10095" title="Methods" titleSpan="4772-4779">
        <section textSpan="4786-6701" title="Subjects" titleSpan="4795-4803"/>
        <section textSpan="6708-8541" title="Intervention" titleSpan="6717-6729"/>
        <section textSpan="8548-10090" title="Statistical analysis" titleSpan="8557-8577"/>
    </section>
    <section textSpan="10100-14921" title="Results" titleSpan="10107-10114"/>
    <section textSpan="14926-21055" title="Discussion" titleSpan="14933-14943"/>
    <section textSpan="21060-23097" title="Back matter" titleSpan="21060-21071"/>
</document>
